<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Rich. Baxter's admonition to Mr. William Eyre of Salisbury; concerning his miscarriages in a book lately written for the justification of infidels, against M. Benj. Woodbridge, M. James Cranford and the author.</title>
            <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B17547</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">49223054</idno>
  <idno type="VID">39618</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240891455</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1181</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206802</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">49223054</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B17547)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39618)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1822:47)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Rich. Baxter's admonition to Mr. William Eyre of Salisbury; concerning his miscarriages in a book lately written for the justification of infidels, against M. Benj. Woodbridge, M. James Cranford and the author.</title>
                  <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 40, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for Thomas Underhill, at the Anchor and Bible ... and Francis Tyton, at the three Daggers ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Woodbridge, Benjamin, 1622-1684.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Cranford, James, d. 1657.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Eyre, William, 1613?-1670. --  Vindicae justificationis gratuitae.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Justification --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39618:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Rich. Baxter</hi>'s ADMONITION TO M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>WILLIAM EYRE</hi> OF SALISBURY; Concerning his MISCARRIAGES in a BOOK lately Written for the Justification of Infidels, AGAINST M. <hi>Benj. Woodbridge,</hi> M. <hi>James Cranford</hi> and the AUTHOR.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Pet. 2.19.</hi>
                  </bibl> While they promise them Liberty, they themselves are the servants of corruption.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 4.22, 23, 24.</hi>
                  </bibl> And <hi>therefore</hi> it was imputed to him for Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. Now it was not written for his sake alone, that it was Imputed to him: But for us also, to whom it shall be imputed, if we Believe on him that raised up Jesus our Lord from the dead.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Ostendisti</hi> tales Discipulos, non <hi>fecisti:</hi> Hoc profecit doctrina tua, ut Peccatum ne Paenitentiam quidem habeat. <bibl>
                  <hi>Hieronym.</hi> contr. <hi>Jovinian.</hi> lib. 2. pag. <hi>(mihi)</hi> 43.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Ʋnderhill,</hi> at the Anchor and Bible in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard near the little North-door, and <hi>Francis Tyton,</hi> at the three Daggers in Fleetstreet near <hi>Dunstans</hi> Church. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:39618:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39618:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Think it not inconvenient to give thee some advertisement of the occasion of this writing. Having met with a Sermon of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>B. Woodbridge</hi> Pastor of <hi>Newbury,</hi> for Justification by faith, and against the Justification of Infidels, I saw so much worth in a narrow room, which caused me to bless God that his Church had such a man, and especially <hi>Newbury</hi> who had so excellently learned a Pastor before, who had mistaken so much in this very Point; and withall in the Epistle of a small Book that I since printed, to commend it to others: M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Eyre</hi> of <hi>Salisbury</hi> was offended it seems at this; and in an Answer to M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> newly published, with an Epistle of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Owens</hi> prefixed, he was pleased to speak of me, what thou hast here Answered.</p>
            <p>In his Epistle against me, he telleth us of one M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Crandon</hi> of <hi>Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire</hi> that [hath now in the Press a large and full Answer to my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxicall Aphorismes.] The Character that M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Eyre</hi> gives of this man is, That he is [a faithfull servant of the Lord Jesus, a workman that needs not to be ashamed,] This is good news if it be true: for then he will not write so many things that deserve shame, as are in this book of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Eyre</hi>'s. But by his wish that others [of more strength and far greater helps] may by him be provoked to shame, I am afraid what the fruit of his Weakness may prove. I confess I have heard neer this twelvemoneth, that this man hath been about this work. The last I heard, informed me, that [he is against the Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Sabbath in Doctrine and Practice notoriously, and one that cals it Legal Preaching to Convince men of sinne and misery, and supposed to be of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Eyre</hi>'s Judgement for the Justification of Unbelievers; and that he having communicated it to M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Eyre,</hi> was
<pb facs="tcp:39618:3"/>gone with him to <hi>London,</hi> to print a large Answer not only to my Aphorismes, but Passages in my other Books; His book about a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred sheets, and some six Shillings price, having more leaves then Arguments, but most liberally pouring forth the Titles of Papist, Jesuite, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is both the Logick and the Rhetorick of it. Also that he had written to the Eminentest Ministers in several Counties, whom he took to be most disaffected to my Aphorismes, to desire them for themselves and friends to take off his Books, which way is much by some distasted. I can say nothing of him of my own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, nor of his Book till I see it. But if these two men be Brethren in a party, and M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Eyre</hi> so much the more esteemed, as I hear; the Reader then may see what to expect by this. I have purposely ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted the Reply to this, that M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Crandon</hi> may before his Book come forth, consider better of some things wherein he shall finde his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther overshot himself, and correct what may tend to his hurt: for I would prevent his sinne. And I do hereby inform thee, Reader, that as soon as ever M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Crandon</hi>'s Book doth come to my hands, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the scope of it is to revile me as a Papist, I purpose to Print a plain Confession of my Faith, and specially how much I ascribe to Works, and how farre I am from Arminianisme also, which these Brethren do accuse me of, and I shall do it in as little room as I can; and then shall leave it to thy choice, whether thou wilt bestow six Pence to understand my true Belief and Profession, or six Shillings and six weeks reading (at least) to have thy ears charmed with the delicions notes of Papist, Jesuit, Arminian, Socinian, and what not of that kinde? If I finde the Book worth the answering, I know not but I may attempt it at large if ever I have time (which is not like,) But if it be according to my information of it, I shall not trouble my self or thee. It is my lot to be troubled by two sorts of men, commonly called Anabaptists and Antinomians, because I was called by God to Vindicate his Truth against them. There came but lately to my hands two of one sort, and the report of a third that are written against me, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Fisher,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Haggar,</hi> and M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Keye;</hi> but when I found them fraught with non-sense and reviling, I laid them by, and never mean to meddle with them more. M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Eyre</hi> and M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Crandon</hi> take the next turn: what one hath done I have seen: what the other will do, I know not but by report. But for my own part, I confess I had a hundred times rather encounter with this party then the former: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I do not apprehend neer so much danger in the opinion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptizing, or not Baptizing Infants, as in the other. I confess this
<pb facs="tcp:39618:3"/>also hath been strangely followed with spiritual Judgements: But I suppose the main cause is, because it openeth the door to Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Contendings, and so Contempt of the Ministry that are against it: but it is hard to see in the nature of the meer Opinions, such hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous evils as we have seen attend it. But for the other, in my Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they do as dangerously subvert the very tenour of the Gospel as well as the Law (and much more) as any Sect that I have known, that hath such men to countenance it. I confess also that I do appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend some more duty lie on us now to resist that way, then hath been ever heretofore: For it was formerly a very rare thing to meet with a man of Learning or considerable Judgement of that way: What men had D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Taylor</hi> to deal with? D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Crisp, Eaton, Town,</hi> were the chiefest Champions since, whom M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Burgess,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Geree,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Bedford</hi> have Confuted. At last <hi>Den, Paul Hobson,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Saltmarsh</hi> took the Chair: The later strangely cryed up by many ignorant souls, and his weakness laid open by that Excellent, Learned, Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Gataker.</hi> But now Libertinism grows into better Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It makes a greater noise in City and Country; yea and men of some name for Learning, are the Patrons of no small portion of it. Lately came forth a Latine Dissertation of <hi>Ludiomaeus Colvinus,</hi> alias, <hi>Ludovicus Molinaeus Med. Doctor</hi> and History Professour in <hi>Oxford,</hi> writted against his own Brother <hi>Cyrus Molinaeus</hi> a Minister. I answered it, before I knew the Authour; and had no sooner fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed it, but I received this of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Eyre</hi>'s. I profess the desire of my soul is so great for the Unity of Brethren and the Churches Peace, that I could heartily wish both contendings and dividing Titles as much as may be laid aside: And therefore for those Reverend Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that hold but the more tolerable part of Antinomianism, I would not have them called by that name. But for the rest, to be tender of the credit of such pernicious errours, and to indulge them by favourable titles, is plainly to betray the Gospel, and mens souls.</p>
            <p>For my part, if I should not preach against the opinion of the Libertines, I could not preach against prophanenesse: When I look back on the Sermons which I preached many years ago, meerly to work mens hearts to Christ, never thinking of the Libertine Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversies, I finde they were the very same things that I am fain to preach now against these Disputers. I was feign to prove to them their natural misery, and that before believing they were children of wrath, and all their sinnes were unpardoned, with the necessity of
<pb facs="tcp:39618:4"/>Faith, Repentance and Confession, for pardon: and the necessity of faithfull Endeavours for the attaining of Salvation; together with the necessity of Renewing Repentance, and begging pardon through the bloud of Christ, when we fall. Lay by all these and such like which the Libertines dispute against, and what have we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most to preach to those that will not have Christ to Reign over them? Truly I finde as farre as I can discern, that most of the prophane people in every Parish where yet I have liv'd, are Antinomians; They are born and bred such; and it is the very natural Religion of men, that have but the advantage to believe traditionally in Christ: I mean, their corrupt nature carrieth them without any teaching to make this use of Christ and the Gospel. And almost all the fuccess of my Labours which hath so much comforted me, hath been in bringing men from natural Antinomianism or Libertinism, to true Repentance and saving Faith in Christ. And therefore should I now side with them, I must unsay what I have been long saying from the plain word of God, to the ungodly that I have preached to. Blessed be God that the Church hath such Writings for plain men to reade, as <hi>Hookers, Boltons, Perkins, Dods, Rogers, Whateleys, Hildershams, &amp;c.</hi> which are written in a sounder strain: Yea that we have such Writings as <hi>Sibbes, Prestons, Baynes,</hi> &amp;c. to shew them, that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences may be Pacified without Antinomianism.</p>
            <p>I am no Prophet; but I confess I am so confident that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency of this Sect will be but of short continuance, that I do not much fear them. For though nature be ready enough to befriend it, yet two disadvantages they runne upon, that will infallibly dash them all in pieces, as soon as the storm of Temptation is allayed. First, They contradict the experiences of the souls of Believers; and the very nature of the New-man is against them: The greatest part of the Spirits work on the Soul is against Libertinism, and the rest against Popery and Pelagianism; supposing the prerequisite foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation laid. And surely the workings of the Spirit are unresistible, and shall bear down these natural conceits before it. The contest be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Gospel and Libertinism in the Church, is like the Contest between the Spirit and the flesh within us, and goes much on the same terms: and Christ will be Conquerour and bring forth Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto Victory, in both. Sound-hearted Christians, that be not only tickled with Sermons, but sanctified by the Spirit, will not long be drawn from such apparent Truths, and sweet and needfull Duties, by the bare names of Free-grace: nor will they deny Free-grace,
<pb facs="tcp:39618:4"/>and the glory of Christs intercession and Kingdom, upon an empty pretence of magnifying his death; when that very magnifying is but a dishonour. A sound-hearted Christian I am perswaded hath some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing within him that potently strives against Libertinism and Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gianism. For example, In prayer, Let a Libertine tell him, [Your sins were all pardoned before you were born, and therefore you must not pray for pardon, but for the Feeling of pardon;] He hath a spirit of prayer within, and a secret impulse to bewail his sinnes, and make out to God for Remission, that will not let him obey those delusions. So if a Pelagian should say [The Power is in thy own Will to please God, and Love and fear him.] The new nature of a Christian doth contradict this, and is inclining him still to beg grace of God, which is a real confession of his own insufficiency. Yea though this Christian should be tainted with either of these Delusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I am perswaded even while speculatively he holdeth them and talks for them, yet other principles lie deeper in his heart, and are secretly working him a contrary way, even to pray for pardon, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Libertine, and for prevailing Grace, contrary to the Pelagian.</p>
            <p>Another Rock the Libertines run against that will shortly dash them all to pieces: and that is [the clear light of express Scripture.] So plainly hath God been pleased to reveal his minde in these cases, that though a few may shut their eyes by prejudice, most will see: and if they are blindfolded a while, it is not like to be long. If all Disputers fail us, as long as plain honest Christians have but recourse to the Word of God, it will convince them at last, and shew them the Errour. For example, in this very Discourse (by one of the rationalest men of that way that I have met with) what plain light doth shine in his face! what palpable abuse is he forced to offer to the Scriptures? So that I dare trust a Reader of any competent judgement and honesty, that is not deeply forestalled, to confute him by the bare reading and observation of the Text. As for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, That to be justified by faith, is to be justified by Christ, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith. So <hi>pag.</hi> 42. he expounds <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. <hi>[That we might be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified by the faith of Christ] i.e.</hi> That it might be manifest that we were justified before we had faith in Christ. But that's common: <hi>pag.</hi> 43. That text <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. which most exactly and purposely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presseth the order of Gods Works, <hi>[Whom he called them he justified]</hi> is put off but thus, 1. The order of words in Scripture do not shew the order and dependance of things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. The Apostle's scope
<pb facs="tcp:39618:5"/>here is not to shew in what order these benefits are bestowed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3. I see no inconvenience at all, in saying that the Apostle here speaks of Justification as declared and terminated in conscience, which some Learned men (M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Owen</hi> and M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Kendall</hi>) do make the <hi>formale</hi> of Justification. But more grossely, <hi>pag.</hi> 44. he expounds <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.24. <hi>[Righteousness shall be imputed to us if we beleeve.]</hi> 1. He saith,
<q>[The particle <hi>[if]</hi> is not conditional, but declarative, describing him to whom the benefit belongs.]</q> Yet one would think that it might hence be gathered at least, that This benefit belongs not to Infidels: But to avoid that too, this is his Paraphrase,
<q>[<hi>q.d.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may know and be assured that Christs righteousness is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> The Apostle saith <hi>[It shall be imputed, if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve.]</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Eyre</hi> saith [We know by this that it was imputed before.] To put the time past for the time present, and a Declarative for a Conditional, is the way of such bold Interpreters, as make their own faith. But tender-conscienc't Christians will not long suffer you so to make their faith, though you may your own.</p>
            <p>Besides such Expositions, the Book contains Conclusions so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary 1. To plain reason: 2. To known Truths in Divinity: 3. To the new nature or inclination of Beleevers: 4. To his own profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions; that though itching ears may be pleased by it, and for the bait of [the name of Free Grace] it may be swallowed down, yet when Judgement, Affection and Practice should digest it, the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble soul will vomit it up again. I will give you but a brief touch of his dealing in the four respects mentioned.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Against common reason and use, he affirms that [If it have any condition, it is not free] and takes M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Walkers</hi> patronage, <hi>p.</hi> 93. and applauds and repeats M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Kendals</hi> gross Discourse, which would give much more of the honour and thanks to the Beleever, then the Giver, and repeats his <hi>Welsh</hi> example, <hi>[God bless her father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who taught her to reade.]</hi> Yea this gross conceit is the very soul of his Discourse; by which it may appear how bruitishly it is animated. But I have proved to him, that a thing may be free that is conditional. <hi>Donatio, Absoluta, Pura,</hi> and <hi>Gratuita</hi> be not all one, or equipollent terms.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And contrary to all sound Divinity, <hi>pag.</hi> 134. he affirms that [Christs death was <hi>solutio ejusdem,</hi> because Christ was held in the same obligation that we were under: <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.3, 4. <hi>He was made under the Law;</hi> not another, but the very same.] Either he means here [the same obligation to duty] or [the same obligation to punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.]
<pb facs="tcp:39618:5"/>If the former, what a proof is here that Christs suffering is <hi>solutio ejusdem?</hi> When the Law obligeth a man to duty, can you thence prove that it obligeth him to punishment? then <hi>Adam</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his fall, and Christ as an innocent creature, and the Angels in heaven are obliged to punishment. But its like he means the later: And then 1. It is most unsound and dangerous doctrine, to say no more: Christs obligation was <hi>sponsionis propriae,</hi> the obligation of Contract or Consent, and as a creature of the special command of his Father thereto: Our obligation is <hi>violatae Legis.</hi> Obligation to punishment is guilt; our guilt was <hi>Reatus culpae &amp; paenae propter cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pam, ex obligatione legis:</hi> Christs guilt is but <hi>Reatus paenae propter cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pam nostram, ex voluntaria susceptione.</hi> Christ was <hi>obligatus ad ean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem paenam</hi> (the same in value) but not, <hi>eadam obligatione.</hi> 2. And how doth <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.3, 4. prove it? Who can think that it means, Christ was made under the curse of the Law? He was indeed made a curse for us by undergoing the penalty; but not said to be made under the curse, nor under the Law as cursing, but as obliging to duty: though its granted that it was part of his humiliation to undertake that task of ceremonious duty.</p>
            <p>So <hi>pag.</hi> 191. he saith,
<q>[Let them consider whether it be more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie for a man that is dead in sin, to believe in Christ, to love God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then it was for <hi>Adam</hi> in his innocency, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to abstain from the fruit of one tree, when he had a thousand besides as good as that: there can be no condition imagined more facile and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sable then <hi>Adams</hi> was.]</q> This is against them that say, Evangelical conditions are easier then Legal works. Where he seems plainly to think, that it was not perfect obedience internal or external that was the condition of Life to <hi>Adam,</hi> but only the not eating of that tree, and so he makes it the easiest thing imaginable. Do you not see how admirably he exalteth the Gospel above the Law, and Christs easie yoak and burden, and his commands that are not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, above that which <hi>Adam</hi> was under? Is it not admirable to see that these men must needs have the new Covenant to have no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, lest it be not free, and those must be cried down as enemies to free Grace, and Legal Preachers, that teach the necessity of faith and repentance to remission of sinnes, when yet the more rigorous Law of nature, <hi>Do this and Live,</hi> the condition of <hi>Adam,</hi> is the most easie imaginable? And what thoughts hath he of <hi>Adams</hi> sin, if he see not the Apostacy from God to the creature, unbelief, and many hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous sins were in it, as well as eating of that Tree?</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:39618:6"/> 3. Against all sound Divinity, and the very sense of a gracious soul, he hath many doctrines which the godly will be ready to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at. As <hi>pag.</hi> 122.
<q>[That the Elect <hi>Corinthians</hi> had no more Right to salvation after their Believing then they had before.]</q> You see in this mans Judgement what we preach for, and what is the state of a natural man, yea of the veriest Rebel, Whoremonger, Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, that is Elect: he may have more knowledge of his happiness after, but he hath no more right to salvation then before. Why say our Divines then that such are not in a state of salvation?</p>
            <p>So <hi>pag.</hi> 103. he saith,
<q>[Though men will not impute or charge sin upon themselves when there is not a Law to convince them of it, yet it follows not but God did impute sin to men before there was any Law promulged, or before the sin was actually committed. For what is Gods hating of a person but his imputing of sin, or his will to punish him for his sin?]</q> Thus Gods preterition or non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>election, called hatred, is confounded with his hatred of Justice and actual displeasure: and God is made to impute sin to the innocent who have no sin, yea to them that are not: When as Imputation of sin is but either the estimation and judging of a sinner to be a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or the adjudication of punishment for that sin, or the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that punishment: all which follow the act of sin; and so he makes Gods act of Imputation to be both <hi>untrue</hi> and unjust; but that indeed he gives the name of Imputation to the eternal Decree, to which God never gave it.</p>
            <p>So <hi>pag.</hi> 61. he saith, concerning all that Christ died for, though yet Infidels and Wicked, that
<q>[Divine Justice cannot charge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them any of their sins, nor inflict upon them <hi>the least</hi> of those punishments which their sins deserve; but contrarily he beholds them as persons perfectly righteous, and accordingly deals with them as such who have no sin at all in his sight.]</q> What humble soul would not tremble to say this of himself now regenerate; much more of the unregenerate? Must God be unjust if he inflict on us the <hi>least punishment</hi> for sin? And yet Scripture says so oft that God punisheth his people, in express words? If it be <hi>paena propter culpam</hi> it is punishment. and is none of your pain, losses, crosses, such? Is not the smalness of your knowledge, love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the remnant of sin, as suffered upon you, a punishment? nor death, nor the bodies remaining in the grave? Are not chastisements a <hi>species</hi> of punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Is not a man punished when he is hang'd for a sin? yea and that by God as well as man? What man dare say, [Lord, if thou
<pb facs="tcp:39618:6"/>hadst laid the least punishment on my body, before Conversion, even in the height of my sin, thou hadst been unjust? yea or if yet thou do it.] Was there no punishment in the dominion of sin, and the want of the sense of Gods favour, which they make to be the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Remission and Justification? The Lord deliver poor souls from such Doctrines as these! Yea so far as they have grace, so far they are delivered. And I hope M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Eyre</hi> speaks against his own heart, by the conduct of his fancy, and the instigation of his contentious passion,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Is it not against his own pretence, that he saith, in his Epistle to the Parliament,
<q>[Though God doth effectually move and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade mens hearts, yet he doth not Necessitate them to believe and embrace the truth.]</q> Would you think and reade this that the man were so zealous against the Arminians, when I, who am called Papist and Arminian, do think, that God doth so effectually move men to believe, as thereby to necessitate them? Though still he doth cause us to do it <hi>liberè,</hi> though <hi>necessariò,</hi> and so necessitate us, as that the act is stil contingent in it self, as from our will.</p>
            <p>So <hi>pag.</hi> 117. he hath these words,
<q>[I dare say, a more unsound Assertion cannot be picked out of the Papists or Arminians, then this is, that faith (taking it as he doth in a proper sense) hath the same place in the Covenant of Grace, as works have in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works.]</q> Where mark, that M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Woodbridge</hi> speaks only of the <hi>place</hi> of faith, and not of the worth, nature, dignity, nor full use, as if it properly or fully had the same office as Works, but the same order in the Covenant. And then see 1. Whether this man doth not make Papists of the generality of the Protestant Churches, and Writers? 2. Or make the Papists as sound as the Protestants. 3. Of what credit this mans word is, that ushers it in with such confidence, [I dare say it,] and whether the reason why he <hi>dares say</hi> that and so many more such things, may not be because he thinks all's par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned already, even before he beleeved. 4. He pretendeth M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Pemble</hi> to be of his Judgement; yet see whether he make not M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Pemble</hi> to hold as unsound doctrine, as any can be picked out of the Writings of Papists or Arminians: I may well bear his heavy charge, when M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Pemble</hi> must bear it, who saies, Treat. of <hi>Justif.</hi> pag. 23. <hi>[There are two Covenants that God hath made with man, By one of which, and by no other means in the world, salvation is to be obtained. The one is the Covenant of Works, the tenour whereof is</hi> [Do this and thou shalt live, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] <hi>The other is the Covenant of Grace, the tenour
<pb facs="tcp:39618:7"/>whereof is</hi> [Beleeve in the Lord Jesus, and thou shalt be saved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] <hi>The condition of this Covenant is Faith.]</hi> And so goes on to shew that the performance and nature of Faith and Works differ; but here gives them the same place of a condition in the Covenant. And <hi>pag.</hi> 22. he saith, <hi>[The condition required in such as shall be partakers of this grace of Justification is true faith, whereunto God hath ordinarily annexed this great priviledge, That by faith and faith only a sinner shall be justified.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So <hi>pag.</hi> 206. he ensnares himself in an objection, which he cannot answer, as I doubt not but M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Woodbridge</hi> will fully shew him, when he hath sifted what is the adequate object of that <hi>Assensus intellectus</hi> and <hi>amplexus voluntatis</hi> which M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Eyre</hi> acknowledgeth. But I must ask pardon of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Woodbridge</hi> for thus anticipating his work. Reader, do but study God and thy own heart, and keep a tender conscience, and an upright life, and a little knowledge more may preserve thee from being a Libertine.</p>
            <p>One thing I forgot, which I now adde, To intreat M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Eyre</hi> and his partakers, to tell me, upon their grounds, Whether God do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the Works as well as the Person of an Elect Infidel? If they say, No: How then are they in Christ, and God perfectly pleased with them? and all the sinfulnesse of those works forgiven? Doth not God accept of that work in which there is no sin imputed? but all pardoned? nothing but the sinfulness can hinder his Acceptance of it? And where then is their vain distinction (that God is pleased with the person and not the work) by which they answer us when we tell them truly, that <hi>Without faith it is impossible to please God? Heb.</hi> 11.6.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:39618:7"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>§. 1.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Defence of my Praises of M</hi>
                        <seg rend="sup">r</seg> Woodbridges <hi>Sermon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of my sleighting all Protestant Divines that differ from me, particularly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> Twiss.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of my Daring as a Dictator to prescribe what men shall reade.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Whether it be true, that with me an Antinomian and an Antipapist are all one?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>About the name Antinomian.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Whether only sins against the light of nature must be punished by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Whether it be no contradiction to have no sin punished but what's a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the light of nature: and yet to have a penalty on them that will call men Antinomians? and not on M</hi>
                        <seg rend="sup">r</seg> E. <hi>for calling Papist?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Whether all the Reformed Churches hold that which I call Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mianism?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Severall slanders of M</hi>
                        <seg rend="sup">r</seg> E. <hi>refuted, About Merit and ascribing to Works.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of my saying Christs satisfaction is</hi> Causa sine quâ non <hi>of Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Gardiners <hi>Positions answered, which M</hi>
                        <seg rend="sup">r</seg> E. <hi>makes like mine.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>§. 2. <hi>Of my Censure of</hi> Maccovius <hi>and others. M</hi>
                  <seg rend="sup">r</seg> Eyre's <hi>testimonies exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined:</hi> Pemble, Rutherford, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>§. 3. <hi>Whether I make all Antinomians that deny Justification by personal Righteousness? and whether I be singular therein?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>§. 4.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>How I deny or hold Christ to be our Material Righteousness? and imputation to be the form of Justification.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of making Christ a</hi> Causa sine quâ non. <hi>More about Merit. M</hi>
                        <seg rend="sup">r</seg> E<seg rend="sup">s</seg>
                        <hi>befriending the Papists.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:39618:8"/>
               <item>§. 5.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>More about our personal Righteousness. My Judgement about Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by our personal Righteousness opened in</hi> 12. <hi>Conclusions.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>M</hi>
                        <seg rend="sup">r</seg> E<seg rend="sup">s</seg>
                        <hi>Arguments against personal Righteousness in Justification an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered:</hi> Paul <hi>excludes not all works: nor all that Debt which is by free Gift of promise, What Justification by Works</hi> Paul <hi>speaks against.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Whether Protestants acknowledging an Evangelical inherent Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, do not</hi> eo nomine <hi>acknowledge that we are Justified by it as far as I do?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>M</hi>
                        <seg rend="sup">r</seg> E. <hi>gives up his Cause, confessing that it is Christ and not we that are the subjects of Justification before we are born: No addition to Christs Righteousness to be Justified by faith or personal Righteousness in subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to it. Imperfect faith may be the Condition of the pardon of its own Imperfections. How faith is taken for the object, in the matter of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>§. 6. <hi>Whether I include Works in Faith?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>§. 7.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>All Conditions are not Moral Causes, no nor any</hi> quà <hi>Conditions.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>M</hi>
                        <seg rend="sup">r</seg> E. <hi>denying Christs death to be the Cause of Gods Justifying, makes it as much a</hi> sine qua non <hi>as ever I did, and much more. He is desired to expedite, How Christs death can be the Meritorious Cause</hi> rei vol tae, <hi>without Causing the</hi> actum volentis? <hi>All the effects of</hi> Electing Love <hi>are not given, by, through and for Christ,</hi> viz. as the Meritorious Cause.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>§. 8. <hi>M</hi>
                  <seg rend="sup">r</seg> E<seg rend="sup">s</seg>
                  <hi>uncharitable Censure of M</hi>
                  <seg rend="sup">r</seg> J. Woodbridge. <hi>How our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines deny Dispositions and preparations to Justification.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>§. 9. <hi>His urging the invincibleness of M</hi>
                  <seg rend="sup">r</seg> Owens <hi>Answer, about Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation being an Immediate effect of Christs death.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>§. 10. <hi>His citation of M</hi>
                  <seg rend="sup">r</seg> Strong. <hi>Proved against him (which may serve to the like of M</hi>
                  <seg rend="sup">r</seg> Owen) <hi>that it is not of necessity that a Condition be</hi> quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad eventum <hi>unknown to the promiser; and that God hath Conditional Promises and Threats though the Condition be foreknown as to the event.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>§. 11.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>M</hi>
                        <seg rend="sup">r</seg> Eyre<hi>'s proved a notorious slanderer, in saying, that the Papists ascribe no more meritoriousness to works then I do,] by the testimony of</hi> Bellarmine, Aquinas, <hi>and M</hi>
                        <seg rend="sup">r</seg> Perkins, <hi>as a tast til I come to M</hi>
                        <seg rend="sup">r</seg> Crand.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Many gross passages of his Book are also opened in the Preface.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39618:8"/>
            <head>§. 1.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Brother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Lately received a Book of your writing (whereof I had before intelligence by the weekly News book) entitled <hi>[Justification without Conditions, or The Free Justification of a sinner]</hi> against M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Woodbridge,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Crauford</hi> and my Self, as Assertors of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Justification.</hi> Your scope is to prove the Justification of Infidels, or of the Elect before Faith, and before they are men, if I understand you. Methinks, there appears in your lines, much more Piety, Candor and Judgement, then I am wont to meet with in men of your Way; though with mixed discoveries of too much defect, especially in the two last. For my own part, I bless God, I have at last learned to love and honour a Christian as a Christian; and therefore all that are Christians; though they have that withall that is displeasing to Christ, and must be so to me. This Debt I confess I owe you; Christ in you is nevertheless Christ, because of your frailties; and though he delay much of the cure of your distempers, I hope he will in due time accomplish it; and when the remnants of your darkness are removed, you will see that truth which now you see not. I ought not to despise you for these infirmities, when I am daily groaning under them my self; and am in the hands of the same Physition; and am so conscious of a necessity of his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der handling. If Christ would not take me with all my faults, and distinguish betwixt his own and mine, between me and my sins, and put up many a thousand provocations, I were lost. And ought I not to honour Christ in you, and see his amiableness through the clouds of such humane frailties, which you as well as your sinfull Brethren, are yet liable to? Yet as Christ loves my sins never the more (that is, hates them nevertheless) for all his incomprehensible love to me, no more will he allow me to love yours. And as I must not think well of them, so neither must I speak well of them. If I should not mistake that for your sinne which is none, I suppose I shall have your free consent to acquaint you with it: And if I mistake not those for your Errours which are none, I suppose you will consent that I warn all those that reade your Book, to take heed of them and reject them. For I suppose you are Virtually contrary to those Opinions which you Actually hold and maintain, and those Practises which Actually you venture to commit. I take it therefore for my duty, as to manifest your Errours with a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to them, because they are against Christ; so with Christian charity to your self, because you intended well, and are Virtually for Christ, even when you do
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39618:9"/>most against him. For I perceive you have a zeal for Christ, though it seems to me, not according to knowledge: And though some of your opinions, I much fear, are destructive of Fundamentals, and would not stand with salvation, if they were fully reduced to practice, yet I perceive great reason of hopes in the rest of your Writings, and by that good which I have heard of you, that you hold them but speculatively, and that in the main you live contrary to the natural tendency of your opinions. I remember therefore that I am writing to a Brother that I must live with in Everlasting Glory, where we shall be both of one minde, when we are perfected in Knowledge: I remember that I am Writing against such sins as are pardoned in the blood of Christ; and as will be very shortly renounced by your self, and against which you will be incomparably more zealous then I can now be, and will speak more disgracefully of them then now I must do. If in the mean time you are confident in the dark, and angry with those that would do you good, yea and abuse them who walk not according to your conceits, it is no wonder, considering what man is, even the best of the Saints while they live in the flesh: Being my self liable to the same distempers, I crave your pardon, if I shall any way injure you in these following lines.</p>
            <p>The substance of your Book I perceive is against M. <hi>Woodbridge;</hi> M. <hi>Cranford</hi> and I are brought in but on the by, but so as that you deal with him but in the beginning, and with me almost throughout. I shall not anticipate M. <hi>Woodbridge,</hi> and therefore intend not the answering of your Book, but to give you a brief account of my thoughts, of so much of it as concerns my self.</p>
            <p>Your first onset is in your third Epistle. My title is <hi>[A leading man in these times:]</hi> when I have neither worldly advantages, nor eminency of Abilities, nor yet opportunities to be much Leading to any but my own Charge. I live I believe as retiredly as you, cloistered up in obscurity, daily exercised with the chastisements of my Lord, and waiting for my change, and minding little to be the Leader of any, further then to help them to heaven to the utmost of my power. And for leading of men into any Parties, from the Unity of Christians, my soul is posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with as deep a detestation of it, as of most sins that the world is guilty of. And I think no man did ever yet come to you, and say, that I once laboured with him to bring him to any private opinion of my own: My Wtitings contain all my fault of that kinde, that I know of. And for them, I desire you and all men to understand me, not as peremptorily affirming every thing that I speak in difficult Controversies, to be infallible Verities, but only as giving you my own opinion of it, and leaving you and all Readers to accept or reject it, according to the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. If what I speak, have evidence of Truth, you cannot darken it by what you say against my person: If it have none, my person hath no advantage, to make my opinion taking with the world.</p>
            <p>The matter which you first charge me with is, my commendation of M. <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi>'s Book in the Epistle to my <hi>Directions for Comfort.</hi> And your self are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to give M. <hi>Woodbridge</hi> your free commendations for the eminency of his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and acquired parts, even to be as <hi>Saul</hi> above his Brethren: and that you seem to confine his worth to these, as if in spirituals the matter were otherwise, will make his cause never the worse before his Judge. You adde that
<q>[It is not to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at that M.B. hath given this superlative <hi>encomium</hi> to M. <hi>Woodbridge</hi>'s Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; he knew well enough that it would rebound upon himself, M. <hi>W.</hi> being a son of his own faith, and this notion of his, but a spark from out of M. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s forge.]</q>
               <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. Thus do bad causes hang together, and the sentences of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:39618:9"/>Oblivious destroy each other. My great imperfections are commonly known: Mr. <hi>W.</hi> you confess to be as <hi>Saul</hi> above his Brethren: What likelihood then of his receiving these things from me? 2. If you speak of the cause in hand, do you seriously think that I am the first that hath said, that <hi>[Infidels are not justified]</hi> or that <hi>[The Elect are not justified till they have faith.]</hi> Think you that Mr. <hi>W.</hi> need to come to such a one as I, to learn that which the Church hath held ever since it was called Christian? 3. Truly I never saw Mr. <hi>Woodbridge,</hi> nor did there ever a message or word in writing pass between us; nay (living here obscurely out of the observation of things remote) I had never to my knowledge heard of him, till I saw his Book. But when I did see, <hi>expede Herculem,</hi> I saw such discoveries in it of a clear understanding, which caused me to bless God for such a man, and in special that you had drawn him out into the world; nor am I sorry much for this your Answer to him, as not doubting but it will draw forth yet more of Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious gifts, which he is furnished with for his Church: I also much rejoyced in that providence of God which had made him successor at <hi>Newbury</hi> to Dr. <hi>Twisse,</hi> giving that people a man so sound, and so able to inform them better, in that one point, wherein the Doctor did so mistake. And indeed Sir, I should take it for a great priviledge, were I near him, to be the Auditor and Scholar of so Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a man; and I doubt not you will finde, that he is well able to manifest your mistakes to the world. And I confess I honour him yet more then I did, since you tell me in this Book (which I knew not before) that Mr. <hi>Parker</hi> was his Grandfather; the name of that man for his Labours and Patience (and especially that excellent Treatise <hi>de Descensu</hi>) being very precious to me. 4. And for your intimation of my self-seeking in commending his Book; you know it is our Masters prerogative to be the Searcher of hearts. Do not you know that an honest man may value those most that are of his own minde? Nay <hi>must</hi> do, <hi>cateris paribus;</hi> for else he cannot value a man for the sake of Gods Truth: For did we not <hi>take</hi> it to be truth, we could not be of that minde our selves. Doth not this raise your estimation of the Learned commender of your Book, and of others whom you oft quote? Would you have envied the praises of Mr. <hi>W.</hi> or his Labours, if he had been of your opinion? Do as you would be done by: Would you have been offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded if I had as much commended you and yours?</p>
            <p>You adde, <q>[I suppose Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s praises or dispraises are not greatly regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by sober-minded Christians, who have observed how highly he magnifies <hi>J. Goodwin</hi> with others of his notion, and how slightingly he mentions Dr. <hi>Twisse</hi> and all our Protestant Divines that differ from him.]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repl.</hi> I confess in respect of ability of judging of mens Learning, and the worth of superlative Divines above my reach, my praise is small addition to any mans honour: But whether my conscience be so small that sober-minded Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans neither <hi>should</hi> nor <hi>do</hi> regard my words, must be determined by my Judge, to whose blessed and more equitable sentence I am approaching. And so farre as I am guilty of Error or partiality, I beg his pardon (for its according to my Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment so to do.) For the high magnifying of <hi>Jo. Goodwin</hi> which you mention, I desire the time and the words may be considered; and then I think he that would then envy him such a commendation, is more partial then I am, though I were as contrary to him as you. I thought it had been only unmannerly language to my Brethren that I had been blamed for: but it seems its praising them too, if it be against the interest of the adverse party. Have you ever heard me praise him for any evil? If you have, speak it out: If not, give me leave to love a Christian as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39618:10"/>a Christian, and a mans Parts and Labours so farre as they deserve, and to honour so much of Christ as I see in any. But how plainly do you still confute your self? You intimate that my commending men is because I am of the same minde: and yet you know or should do, that I do in that very place profess my own Judgement to be contrary to that of Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> and the rest there named, and that I only reprehend men for their bitterness and contempt of them. Now Sir, if your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science will warrant you in such dealing as this, to say I commend men as <hi>of my notion,</hi> (if you mean mine) even when I purposely express my opinion to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, and write against theirs, it is not of the same complexion as mine is, as bad as I am.</p>
            <p>And as little truth is there in your words of my slighting Dr. <hi>Twiss,</hi> yea and all our Protestant Divines! Which be the words Sir that are guilty of that charge? For Dr. <hi>Twiss</hi> I have honoured few men living more formerly; and much honour his Name and Labours still; though I rejoyce that I am got out of the snare of one or two of his Mistakes. You are no Papist I hope; and therefore do not think a man slighted that is not taken to be infallible, or perfect. But of this I have said enough to Mr. <hi>Kendall.</hi> The rest of your Accusation, (as to all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Divines that differ from me) is either a breach of the ninth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or else my Tongue or Pen hath somewhere spoken quite contrary to my heart.</p>
            <p>I marvell at your next speeches, that
<q>[Mr. <hi>W.</hi> throughout all his Sermon, never so much as hinted, how or in what sense we are justified by faith.]</q> When<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he doth it as solidly (in my weak judgement) as ever I read in any Divine? Nay when your self bestow some labour to confute him: Doth he not tell you it justifies us by the way of a condition, though Naturally Active, yet Morally as it were Passive, qualifying us for Gods free Justification by his Covenant? To this purpose, but more largely, I well remember he speaks. How then durst you say, and publish to the world, that he never hinted how or in what sense we are justified by faith? Sure Brother, this is not well done.</p>
            <p>Next you say of me, that
<q>[His advice to all Christians to buy one of these Sermons, argues rather his conceit of himself, then his charity to them.]</q>
               <hi>Repl.</hi> Both these sins, self-conceitedness and want of charity, are latent in the heart, and by the Searcher of hearts it is that I must be tried, whose high prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, my opinion is, you should not usurp. Truly Brother, I have as much reason to value Truth, so far as I know it, as you or other men: and as little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son as many to be byassed in my seeking it. I dare say, I dearly love it, and that the searching for it doth cost me somewhat? If I know it not, it is not because I would not know it if I could. It is my hourly studied, and daily prayers, and if I knew any other lawfull possible way to attain it, how gladly would I use it, though it were to the loss of all I have in the world, or though the Truth were contrary to my former opinions, or though it would subject me to the ha; red of my dearest friends! He that knows my heart, knows that I speak my heart, if I know it my self. Nor do I take this for any high commendations; for mans intellect (as <hi>participativè</hi> voluntary) doth Will Truth as its proper natural object. I mean, it would know things as they are (where carnal interest and enmity causeth not the perverting of the soul herein.) And I do not finde in my <hi>flesh</hi> the least opposition to your opinion.</p>
            <p>Where you adde your reason
<q>[That he dares take upon him the Office of a Universal Dictator to prescribe not only to his <hi>Kederminsterians,</hi> but to all private
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39618:10"/>Christians what Books they shall reade.]</q>
               <hi>Repl.</hi> If by <hi>[prescribing]</hi> you mean [commanding] all men know that I am no Commander, and therefore my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands were more likely to be derided then obeyed. If you mean [advifing] Why may I not dare to do that? Is that the work of a Dictator? If I may advise in other points of duty, I know not why I may not do the like in this. I have advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to the reading of other Books (as flat, I think, against your opinion) <hi>Bolton, Perkins, Hooker, Preston,</hi> &amp;c. yet none ever charged me with [daring to prescribe as a Dictator.] However you know my word will not take much, and therefore you need not be so much offended. And for all the distinctions which you are pleased to take as Herring-bones, I doubt not but to mean Christians, that Book may be profitable: and that may prove happy food to others, which you call <hi>Poison.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You adde
<q>[As for the title of Antinomianism which he bestows upon our doctrine, it is no great slander out of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s mouth, with whom an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinomian and an Antipapist are <hi>termini convertibiles.</hi>]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. To begin with your last because it is the reason of the former: It is written, <hi>Thou shalt not hate thy brother in thy heart, but shalt in any wise rebuke thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and not suffer sin upon him,</hi> Lev. 19.17. I perceive by your words that you are Pastor of a Gathered Church (as it's call'd) were I one of your neer communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I should openly desire satisfaction concerning these words, not as to my self for the wrong, but as to the Church, that otherwise if you prove impenitent, we might avoid you. My reasons are, because God hath faid, <hi>Thou shalt not bear false witness against thy neighbour.</hi> And <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.11. <hi>Ye shall not steal, neither deal falsly, neither lye one to another.</hi> Deut. 19.18, 19. <hi>Behold, if the witness be a false witness, and hath testified falsly against his brother; then shall ye do unto him as he had thought to have done unto his brother.</hi> And I suppose you would avoid communion with a Papist, and have men so to do. <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.16, 19. <hi>Six things doth the Lord hate, yea seven are abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to him: A proud look, a lying tongue,—a false witness that speaketh lies, and him that soweth discord among brethren.</hi> Prov. 19.5. <hi>A false witness shall not be unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, and he that speaketh lies shall not escape.</hi> So <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.5. &amp; 12.17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15. <hi>Without are— and whosoever loveth and maketh a lye,</hi> Psal. 15.1, 2, 3. <hi>Lord who shall abide in thy Tabernacle? who shall dwell in thy holy Hill? He that walketh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly and worketh righteousness, and speaketh the truth in his heart.</hi> Now as to the fact I prove it thus: If with me an Antipapist and an Antinomian be <hi>termini con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertibiles,</hi> or all one, then I take all Antipapists for Antinomians. But the later is false: Therefore so is the former. All the Churches of <hi>France, Belgia, Bohemia, Helvetia, Scotland, England,</hi> &amp;c. who subscribed the Harmony of Confessions, or owned them: All our Reverend Assemblies that made the late Confession of Faith and Catechisms, and all that own them: All that subscribed the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> I take for Antipapists, and yet I take them not for Antinomians, no nor any man for an Antinomian who believeth any one of all these: Therefore I take not all Antipapists for Antinomians. Again, either you speak of my heart or of my language. For the later, shew where, or prove when I said that Antipapists and Antinomians are <hi>termini convertibiles,</hi> expresly or implicitly, and then call me a slanderer and spare not. If you speak of my Thoughts, I know them better then you, and I profess them to be otherwise. Nay in the very particulars wherein I differ or seem to differ from my Brethren, I have received large Animadversions from very many Learned men, and I profess to take not one of them all for an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinomian. So much for your ground-work. Now to your structure.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:39618:11"/>
            <p> As for the term [Antinomian] I confess I think it more fitly applied to the Practice of those whom I have known, of that way, then to their Doctrine: For whereas the name is taken from one of the least of their great Errors, it should have rather been taken from the greater. For my part I heartily wish that among those whose opinions unfit them not for the Communion of Saints, and suffice not to Excommunicate them, all names of Parties or of Reproach were utterly laid aside; and would willingly contribute my best endeavours to that end, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily joyn with you in your motion to the Parliament that a Penalty might restrain such Dividing wayes. But yet 1. while men go commonly under such a name, we can scarce tell how to make known whom we speak of, but by the name or a description equipollent. 2. And I take a full Antinomian to be one that is unfit for Christian communion, as subverting the very substance of Christian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. But I confess I think it fitter to call them Antigospellers, or Antichristian, or Libertines, then Antinomians: And because it is the old and fit name, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after I will use rather the name of <hi>Libertines.</hi> But for sober moderate men, which are but half Antinomians, holding but the less dangerous part of their opinions, and disclaiming the rest, (though they are shrewdly concatenated) and not see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the rest do follow them, truly, as I dare not disaffect them, nor would avoid communion with them, so neither would I have them called Antinomians, further then to themselves to convince them of their participation in that sinfull way, as the name may be used in a course of arguing. And of these I hope you are one: and I hope it is no worse with some of your partakers.</p>
            <p>But Sir, methinks you have some very strange passages in your Epistle Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory about these things: I would warn you to search your heart whether the later part of the second page of that Epistle, be not the venting of pure malice; and a trampling upon men that have more to say against you, then you seem to take notice of. But the thing I mean is 1. Your most dangerous doctrine. 2. Your most palpable self-contradiction by word and deed. 1. In the bottom of the third page in your parenthesis
<q>[Nor can I excuse their connivence at any of those evils that are contrary to the Law of nature.]</q> You seem to teach that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate should punish no other evils; for these words, following a discourse against force in matter of Religion, can bear no other sense that I know of. But is this your friendship to Christ, that you would have the Magistrate be indifferent to him and Mahomet or Antichrist? What? not command the preaching of Christ? and punish the neglect of it in those that should do it? Nor hinder men from preaching against Christ, or calling him a Deceiver, or blaspheming the holy Ghost? nor for preaching up Mahomet? Is this your friendship to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as to draw them into such a guilt, which would cause God to curse them and cast them out, and make their names hatefull to the Christian world? Is this your love to the Churches of Christ, that you would have this deluge of guilt and confusion let in upon us? Methinks the very thoughts of such a dolefull state of the Church, should make your heart sad! Is this your love to your native Land, to open upon it such a Floodgate of desolation? And is this your love to the souls of men to prostitute them to all deluders? If you think that truth is so discer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to good and bad, that if all may but speak there is no great danger; do but open your eyes and Judge by the experience which these times afford you! You can scarce get men to receive the truth that hear none contradicting it: How much less when they have ten speaking against it, for one that speaks for it, and that with such subtilty as they cannot resist?</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:39618:11"/>
            <p> Nay, Sir, I had hoped that you who do so let fly at me as a Papist, would not have proved such a friend to Popery. Would you have Popery have Liberty in <hi>England</hi> again in all the Points of it that are not against the Light of Nature? Truly you shew me but what I saw before! that all over-doing is undoing! and that none would sooner let in Popery then those that fly to the contrary extream. But shall I tell you Sir; If once they have full liberty here as you have, I think you will finde, that their numbers and prevalency will cloud your Sect, and all the rest of the Sects in <hi>England.</hi> And as very a Papist as I am, I would far rather joyn with you to keep them out; and would intreat you for the Peace of your own Conscience that you would unsay this again, and write a recantation of it to the Parliament.</p>
            <p>I would have you also to consider your strange Contradictions to your own words.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You would have Names of Obloquy, and in particular that of <hi>Antinomians,</hi> restrained by Penalties. But is it against the light of nature for a man that is in Judgement against you, to call you Antinomian? If the Religion or doctrine may be tolerated, why may not the Naming of men accordingly? You will allow men to Do Evil, but not to be called Evil Doers? Where the Light of Nature reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the Thing, me thinks it should not reach the Name! He that should judge you a Heretick, and thinks it his duty to make it known, seeth not by the light of Nature that he may not Call you so.</p>
            <p n="2">2. May not the Lord Jesus (for whom you seem zealous) have some of that favour from you, or respect, or tenderness of his Name and Honour, which you would have your self? If the Parliament must lay a Penalty on them that will call you Antinomian, I pray you put in one word with it, that they may lay a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty on any that will Call Christ a Deceiver, or reproach his Holy Name, or doctrine, or wayes; or would set up Mahomet or Antichrist against him; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be against the light of Nature or no. At least it is against the light of Nature to despise God: and Christ saith, <hi>He that despiseth you</hi> (his Ministers) <hi>despiseth me, and he that despiseth me, despiseth him that sent me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. If all those Names must be restrayned by Penalties, then I doubt the Name of Papist must be restrayned, and Socinian too: And would you indeed have a Law made to punish all that call men Papists or Socinians? and yet seem so zealous against them. Still the <hi>Overdoing</hi> Enemies, are the greatest friends, to Popery and other Errors.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But how comes it to pass that I must be so frequently with you a Papist, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian, Arminian, and yet it is a sin to be restrayned by Penalties to use Names of obloquy? But you shew us plainly what kinde of Liberty of Conscience it is that men are now for: A Liberty for them and others to abuse Christ, his truth, and their Brethren: but a restraint of speaking against their reputation. It seems though you speak generally, it was the Name of Antinomian or Libertine that you meant. Truly Sir, though M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Woodbridge,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Cranford</hi> and I, deserve not so much respect at your hands, yet me thinks the Parliament deserved sounder advice, and better and more carefull language of you then this: You should not have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spoken them with such Contradictions and dangerous Intimations.</p>
            <p>You proceed with me thus <q>[Let him shew us any one Church or single per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, accounted Orthodox, till this present age, that did not hold some, yea most of those Points which he cals Antinomianism, and I will openly acknowledge I have done him wrong: otherwise let him be looked upon as a slanderer and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39618:12"/>reviler of all the Protestant Churches, who under a shew of friendship, hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to expose them to the scorn and obloquy of their enemies.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repl.</hi> I willingly stand to your motion: But I must needs say, that the tempter hath much foiled you, when he prevailed with you to write these and the following words! and to add impudency to falshood and slander: for so it is. You should have cited my words which you lay this charge upon, or else I know not what to vindicate; for I know not what you mean. But observe, that the question between us is not, Whether any of the reformed Churches do differ from me in any thing, or Whether I erre therein? But, Whether they hold any, yea most of those opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions which I call Antinomianisme? Would you make men believe that all the Protestant Churches are of your opinion? This is to put out mens eyes, and bid them renounce both sense and reason. I will call no man. Antinomian that doth hold the doctrines of the most Imperfect Confession in all the Harmony: Nay, I provoke you if you are able to name one man in the first, second, third, fourth or fifth Century, yea or for a thousand if not fourteen hundred years after Christ, that held any two, yea one, of the opinions which I ever call'd Antinomianism, except it were some that were notorious Hereticks. Till then, I suppose it is not the Accused, but the Accuser that is reputed the Calumniator till he make good his charge.</p>
            <p>You proceed, <q>[Mr. <hi>B.</hi> (the better to ingage his Reader), tels him his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is of a middle strain, as if all the reformed Churches had hitherto been in an extream, in this fundamentall point of our Justification.]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. Though Justification be a fundamentall, yet so is not every point that concerneth it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I hope you will not perswade us that all the Protestant Churches are for the Justification of Infidels! unless it be by taking the name of Protestant Churches from all that will not say as you.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What Divine of note can you name, but doth in one thing or other, differ from the greater part? I think but few. Yet we do not for that one Point sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate him from the rest. And let me add to the former Section, that if it be proved of any one or more of our Divines, that they hold one or two lesser points of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomianisme, I think it not fit therefore to call them Antinomians. I will not call <hi>Zanchy</hi> a Papist, because he denied the Pope to be the Antichrist: or because of his so much differencing <hi>Johns</hi> Baptisme and Christs: nor will I call him an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptist, because he thought that those in <hi>Acts</hi> 19. were twice baptized, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging so many Fathers of his minde. The like I may say of many another.</p>
            <p n="4">4. No wonder if any doctrine that avoideth your extream be contemned by you: It hath alway been so with men in extreams. But the day is coming when Moderation and Truth (which lieth between extreams) will be better regarded.</p>
            <p n="5">5. As for my [engaging my Reader] which you talk of; I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it discover more of the secrets of your own heart or mine: sure I am you know not mine, but should know your own: And if you speak according to yours, I will speak according to mine, and thats this; that I love Gods Truth, and therefore would propagate it; and I love mens souls, and therefore would do them all the good that I can: but for any advantage that I aim at to my self by <hi>engaging</hi> men to me, besides the doing of my duty, I yet know it not. Nay I must needs reckon upon the loss of mens esteem before I resolve to cross them in their opinions.</p>
            <p>You proceed like the rest <q>[I am sure he gives as much unto Works and less unto Christ then the Papists do.]</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:39618:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep. A false witness shall not be unpunished, and be that speaketh lies shall not escape, Prov.</hi> 19.5. Review the texts before cited. Truly, Sir, I cannot think you durst sin thus without shame and fear, if you had not been hardened in security, by thinking your sins were forgiven before you were born! What good will all your Arguments do to prove to any man, that your doctrine encourageth not men in sin, while they shall see you run on in it so boldly? What hear we <hi>words</hi> for, when we see contrary <hi>deeds?</hi> As the Papists have done as much against their Religion, by Powder plots, Treasons, lying, as by their very erroneous doctrines, among those that judge by such experiences; so have the men of your sect done, to the wonder of observers. Whether your words here be true or not, I shall refer the Reader to my Reply to Mr. <hi>Crandon,</hi> whither I reserve it.</p>
            <p>You add <q>[He makes Works by Virtue of Gods Promises and Covenant, to be the meritorious Causes of Justification and Salvation, and in no other sense do the Papists affirm it.]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep. Thou shalt not bear false witness against thy neighbour.</hi> It is a harsh provoking kind of answering, for to give a brother a plain <hi>mentiris:</hi> and therefore I love not to deal with those sayings, that will admit of no other answer in termes or sense. If the ninth Commandment be Law, then this practice of yours is Antinomian. Produce that place; express those words of mine, which may make good this charge. I have ever professed that our best works are not in the least degree meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, no not of a bit of bread, much less of Justification and Salvation. There never fell from my Pen such a word as you charge me with, and yet you dare do it. One would think that common wit should have told you, that when the falshood of such passages <hi>de facto</hi> are discovered, it should redound to your own shame, and consequently to the great prejudice of your Cause. Nay I durst not acknowledge any Causality in faith to our Justification, and therefore in that Point adventured to differ from many Brethren: Yet doth this man say, that I [<hi>make Works by Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Gods Promise and Covenant, meritorious Causes of Justification.</hi> And mark what an occasion he takes of this slander. In the 26. <hi>Thes.</hi> of my <hi>Aphor.</hi> I purposely speak against the doctrine of Merit; shewing that properly no works of ours can be called Meritorious, but in the end did concede that Improperly they may: This I did, because the Fathers for many hundred years after Christ use the word <hi>Merit,</hi> in application to mans works; and because all our Divines that ever I read against the Papists, <hi>nemine contradicente,</hi> do answer that the Fathers used the word <hi>Merit</hi> improperly. But these three things I ever professed in speech and writing on all occasions. 1. That no acts or works of ours are Meritorious Causes of sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, much less of Justification. 2. That therefore the word Merit cannot be applied to them, but Improperly. 3. That therefore it is not fit to use so much as the word. And though when we read it in the Councils or Fathers, we must in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret it with a due reverence to them, yet is it fit to be excluded among our selves. Yet should I meet with any godly, sober man of a contrary judgement, that thought the name might be used while he interprets it in the same sense which the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches hold, I would not approve of that mans opinion of the use of the word, but yet I would not for the bare word pretend that we are of different Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions, or do differ in the Thing which he expresseth by that word, I should think it very unjust if I should report all of my brother, which may be said of him Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly. If <hi>David</hi> say, <hi>All men are Lyars,</hi> meaning, not able to help in time of need, and therefore not to be trusted in, as being fallacious; may I therefore call every man that I speak with a Liar? What is there that may not be spoken of you
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39618:13"/>truly in Impropriety? But suppose you would have made the worst of my words that malice could have done without express falshood, should you not then have taken up with my own words, without the addition of your forgeries? I said that [This is Improperly called Merit,] But I never said that [our works are the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious Causes of Justification or salvation.] For as I have still maintained that they are No Causes at all, so in saying that they are called Merit Improperly, I say, they are no Causes Meritorious: no more then a <hi>Causa fine qua non</hi> is a true Cause, because it is Improperly so called. Nay I never once said, that as to our Justification begun, that works are so much as existent, but alwaies maintained that we are truly and fully as from all sins past Justified by faith, before Works of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall obedience are in being.</p>
            <p>The next words ["and in no other sense do the Papists affirm it,] is another notorious falshood: which if it were in Doctrinals only, I could answer it with a cold <hi>Negatur;</hi> but thus to multiply falshoods one after another, seems a sad practice from a godly man. He might well know, if indeed he know what the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists hold, that they are of several parties among themselves differing about this Point, yet all of them except <hi>Waldensis,</hi> or very few more, do maintain the fitness of the word Merit: most assert both Merit of Congruity before Regeneration, and Merit of Condignity after; and <hi>Scotus</hi> and a few more that reduce all to the right by promise are rejected by the rest, who affirm a Merit of value or proportion: And our own Divines generally approve of them that hold only <hi>Meritum ex pacto,</hi> as to the thing, denying only the fitness of the name, and that this is any proper Merit. This all Divines know to be true that have read the Papists writings and ours against them. And yet this man did not fear to say, that [in no other sense do the Papists affirm it,] yea and that I [give as much to Works and less to Christ then the Papists:] I shall purposely delay my particular proof of the contrary till I speak to M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Crandon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay a little before he saith of me <q>[Its like he thinks, that the Papists are much neerer the line of truth then any of them,]</q>
               <hi>i. e.</hi> of all the Protestant Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. Here are two sins as evident as his sense, <hi>viz.</hi> false-speaking and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleness.</p>
            <p>A little before he said, he <q>[feareth the men of <hi>Kederminster</hi> are fed but with lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle better food,]</q> yet did this man never hear me preach, never see my face, and yet can censure my teaching! Nay had he but enquired of me, he might have learned how little I meddle with Controversie in the Pulpit: Or if I did, and did all erroneously, yet I read the Scripture to them, I publish the doctrine of the Creed and Catechisme, is all this <hi>poison or ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aky meat</hi> as he speaks? Judge of the affection and practice of this man by the Apostles marks, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3, 4, 5, 6, 7. and see what Charity he hath: <hi>Charity thinketh no evil:</hi> But how much of his own sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mising hath he vented in a few lines? And yet he proceeds as fresh and fearless as before.</p>
            <p>For he adds <q>[I must needs say, I never met with that Papist, which cals Christ a <hi>fine qua non</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> a Cause which effects nothing) of our Justification.]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Would you not think here that the man did intimate that I say this, and but this of Christ? But mark the Case. In <hi>Thes.</hi> 56. <hi>p.</hi> 215. I speak only of Christs satisfaction, and not of any other work of Christ: And I say that it hath several waies of Causing our Justification. 1. That it is the Meritorious Cause, I say, I know few but Socinians will deny. 2. That it is also the Principal Cause <hi>fine qua non,</hi> as Removing Impediments: withall I shew, that I so call it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39618:13"/>only in respect of its Physical operation, but as to Moral Dignity, I plead for its preheminence. Now what doth this man but lay down this word alone, that I call Christ the <hi>Causa sine qua non,</hi> and leave out that I call his satisfaction the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious Cause, and allow it the preheminence in Moral respect. Nay mark that himself makes Iustification to be from Eternity, and not at all Caused or procured by Christs death <hi>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad actum volentis,</hi> but only <hi>quoad rem volitam:</hi> And let any man tell me what he can possibly ascribe to Christs satisfaction on those terms more then I do in the place that he carps at. Those things that are but <hi>Causa sine qua non in sensu physico,</hi> are of singular Moral Causality, and so I shewed that Christs death is; but that faith is so a <hi>causa sine qua non,</hi> as to have no Moral Causality at all, as being but the Accepting of a free Gift. These things are so far from Popery, that they accord with the opinions of his own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, as expressed hereabouts, and yet this man saith he never met with Papist that said so.</p>
            <p>He next proceeds to compare my doctrine with some Positions of <hi>Gardiners</hi> in <hi>Foxes Martyrology.</hi> I have not the book at this time in my study to examine his dealing, but to his Positions I shall answer particularly, thus. 1. All the effects of Christs Passion have not a Condition: The satisfaction of Iustice, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the New Covenant, the sealing it with Miracles, the publishing it to the world, and preaching it now to any Nation or Person, and the first Grace of faith and repentance; all these are given absolutely, and not made over upon any Condition on mans part. But Iustification, Remission, Adoption and Salvation, are given Conditionally 2. His second Position hath its answer in the first, 3. The third is false; for faith is the Condition it self, and not somewhat ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent by which we must know it, unless he speak of any common faith which helpeth a man to perceive the need of saving faith; or unless he speak of the Condition of our Glorification or Iustification as consummate, which is sincere obedience, in subserviency to faith and concomitancy with it. 4. To the fourth, I will believe that faith is the Gift of God, if all the Papists living believe it, and that by this Gift, I do well in believing in order of nature, but not of time, before I am Justified. 5. And so that I do well toward the attainment of Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; But not of justification in the Popish sense, which comprehendeth san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification even in the first act, for so I do not well before it, so as any of my actions are Accepted of God in Christ, and their infirmities pardoned; but only as an unbeliever may comparatively be said to do wel in coming to hear the word, rather then in going to an Alehouse. 6. I believe that Faith and Charity thrive together, I am a Papist if this be Popery; that Faith works by Love. I do not think it sound doctrine, that to the Attainment of justification is required Faith and Charity, without limitations and explication: For though a Love to Christ the Object is effential to that Faith that must accept him (for let men say what they will, Christ must be accepted as Good, and Good cannot be accepted without Love,) yet Charity usually signifies that Grace, as extended to all other objects of Love, as well as an offered Christ, and so the Proposition is false un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood of our first being justified, as the word <hi>Attainment</hi> shews it is. 8. The eighth Proposition is false. If only the beginning be free, then the rest is not free, 9. The ninth is answered in the former. 10. The tenth I never heard Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant deny in <hi>sensu diviso;</hi> I believe that God gives the grace of Repentance to men in deadly sin, even to all that have it, and I know not else how they should have it, and that this Repentance is a Condition of justification, in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39618:14"/>sense, but not in the Popish sense, that is, of the first renewing of our natures. And now Brother I would I had given you all I have in the world, yea twenty lives, if I had so many to lay down, on condition you could but make it good, that the Papists erre no more then this; yea no more then these words of <hi>Gardiners</hi> in their obvious sense. But if you would be believed in crediting the Papists, you must get you Readers that never read their writings, or that have read none but such as the late <hi>Christian Moderator,</hi> that tells you by Merit they mean nothing but rewardableness. If you will make all the Papists Orthodox to prove me a Papist, youl shew how much your extremities hurt their Cause. For my part I say again, would I had lost my life so that it were true. I would no more remove from the truth because the Papists own it, then I would deny God because they profess him. And if you can make me believe that the Papists are as Orthodox men as you pretend them to be, you will but exceedingly glad my heart, and not a whit remove me from my own opinion. These be but words to affright such children that receive their faith on the credit of man, and that must know what the Papists hold, that they may be contrary, before they can tell what to hold themselves. These move not men that wait for the Law at the mouth of Christ, and that attend the Spirit of Illumination by the study of the word, and go to the Law and to the Testimony, and call no man Master on earth. The worst you can do by such Toyes of malice, are but to diminish my reputation, with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious men, that follow parties for their faith, and know not what the Unity of the faith means, nor what it is to depend for teaching upon Christ. Though these men may be godly and zealous, and such as I dearly love, yet were it not for being made uncapable of doing them good, and diminishing Gods interest and their benefit, by the diminution of mine, I think you would not much assault me with these weapons, if you knew how little I value their esteem, when I cannot have it with Innocency and Truth. Brother, I am proud and sinful the Lord knows as well as others: but yet I can truly say, that I have bent my studies and vigilancy against the sin of pride above most others, for divers years past, and that I have stood so long on the brink of the grave and the door of eternity, that I can with very little trouble bear all the quarrels and contrempts of men. How small a matter is it to me to be judged by man, who am daily looking to be called to the bar of God? I am almost out of this wrangling censorious world, and know its Gods Approbation which I must stand by, and then think of me all as you please; if God justifie me, I care not for your condemning me. But you proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <q>[And for his choice notion of Justification by Works as they are our new Covenant-Righteousness, I find it was a shift of the Papists long ago, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> You are very unfit to parallel the Papists and me, who for ought I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive understand neither of us I need not tell Divines that read them, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists opinion but for my own, I say still, that we are justified first, without so much as the presence of Works, and finally without their Causality: but yet had rather expound <hi>James,</hi> then deny the truth of his words. Nor do I acknowledge any Universall Righteousness but Christs, consisting in the remission of sins. Onely I think not that Christ died to pardon my Faith and Love, as such, but to pardon the infirmity of them: to forgive my sins, as sins, and not my duty, as duty, and therefore that we have a particular Righteousness by which in subordination to Christs, as being only the Condition of our Enjoying it, we may be said to be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified. But of these things more fully God willing hereafter.</p>
            <p>He adds <q>[I shall not trace Mr. <hi>B.</hi> any further, there being now in the Press,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39618:14"/>as I am informed, a large and full Answer to his Paradoxicall Aphorisms, by a faithful servant of the Lord Iesus, Mr. <hi>Crandon</hi> of <hi>Fawley</hi> in <hi>Hampshire,</hi> a Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that need not be ashamed.]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Of this book I have spoke in the Epistle enough. Why speak you of it as a strange matter [as I am informed?] Its long since I was informed of your being with him at <hi>London,</hi> as combined together in the same Cause, and promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting each others work; one against Mr. <hi>troodbridge,</hi> the other against me.</p>
            <p>Your next shews your modesty, in calling such books <q>[far more dangerous then the Ranters Blasphemous Pamphlets]</q> and imitating that they are Popish and Arminian, and how <hi>Reignolds, Whittakers, Davenant, Prideaux</hi> would not have endured them.] Would you make the world believe that these men were of your minde for the Iustification of Infidels? Truly if you will be of the same minde as these men were, though I may differ from you in some point of Method or Words, yet I will never oppose you nor write against you, if you wil but give me leave to forbear. My differences with these men are nothing to my differences with you. Nay you might have known if you would, that <hi>Davenant</hi> maintains the Conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality of sincere obedience to the Continuance of our Iustification in the same terms as I do. And so much to your Epistle. Now to your Treatise.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <head>§. 2.</head>
            <p>THe first place that I observe you falling on me, is <hi>Pag.</hi> 25. about <hi>Maccovius,</hi> where you say <q>[Though one of our late writers, (Mr <hi>B. App. p.</hi> 147.) men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions this Doctors opinion with much contempt and oscitancy, calling his As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertions strange, sensless and abhorred (which is the less to be regarded) seeing he usually metes out the same measure unto all men else, whose Notions do not square with his own mold.]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep. Thou shalt not bear false witness against thy neighbour.</hi> My words of <hi>Maccovius</hi> doctrine I refer to the consideration of any that are impartial: for my part I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not repent of them, any more then for saying that whoredom or drunkenness are to be abhorred. But that I [usually mete out the same measure to all men else whose Notions square not with my mold,] is a gross untruth, which any man that converseth with me, and hath read my writings, may quickly know. But let's hear your proof.</p>
            <p>
               <q>[As Dr. <hi>Twiss, Mr. Walker,</hi> and them that hold the Imputation of Christs active Righteousness whom he calls, A sort of Ignorant and unstudied Divines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Divers more gross falshoods in these few words, are added to the rest. I am loath to call you Antinomian, but if the ninth Commandment be Law, I am sure you make as bold to break it, if that be Antinomianism, as most that I have dealt with. 1. Why did you not quote the place where I [mete out the same measure] to Dr. <hi>Twiss?</hi> Mr. <hi>Kindal</hi> accuseth me of sleighting him indeed; and what is my language? why I call him [that most excellent famous Divine.] But I judge him to mistake in saying Remission of sin is from eternity: that is, I judge him not Infallible nor free from error: Thus Protestants abuse all men, and Papists all save the Pope and his General Council. 2. For Mr. <hi>Walker,</hi> I confess I spoke undiscreetly, as having no call to meddle with him, and I hereby revoke it, and do repent it, that I intimated him to be <hi>Ignorant,</hi> and that I medled with his <hi>Reviling<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:39618:15"/>But yet I will take no man for a competent Judge of my fault, that hath not read his Book against Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gatakers</hi> Book against him in Defence of Mr. <hi>Wotton.</hi> 3. It is here intimated, that the cause of my speech was his differing from my mold: that is, as he means my opinions (for indeed the Scripture is my mold: Whereas the reason of my words against Mr. <hi>Walker,</hi> was his exceeding hard language to his Brethren; which as being against love and peace, I so far reprehended, as to say [He strongly reviled and weakly disputed] when in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course and Pulpit he had done so much for above 20 years, against such learned, choice servants of God, as Mr. <hi>Wotton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bradshaw,</hi> &amp;c. and when in the Press the term Heretick, Blasphemer, &amp;c. are so familiar; and he even proceeds to the Curse of Anathema Maran-atha. But what if I spoke unreverendly to this Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend man, in saying he Beviled? is it just that I be accused of doing so to all men, or any others, when I never was guilty? 4. Next I am charged with the like, as to ["them that hold the Imputation of Christs active Righteousness.] Another falshood, as thus without limitation expressed: For I there professed to hold it my self, as part of satisfaction, and I hold it as Meritorious of all that higher felicity then the first Covenant gave (if there by any such:) But it was only one sort or sense of Imputation there explained which I spoke against. 5. Another untruth it is, that I [call these, A sort of ignorant unstudied Divines:] The words are these <q>[The maintainers of it, beside some Able men, are the vulgar sort of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>studied Divines, who having not ability or diligence to search deep into so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found a Controversie, do still hold that opinion which is most common and in credit.]</q> Where I divide those that are for this way into two sorts: some Able men, and others the common unstudied Divines that take it on credit: And this is a known truth that too many such there are, that so receive even much of their Religion: As if you did not think so your self of the most that are against your particular opinion? Do you not think they go for company against you? So I do not call all <hi>Ignorant</hi> that go that way, nor any man because he goes that way.</p>
            <p>You add of <hi>Maccovius</hi>
               <q>[I dare say his Arguments in this particular will not seem so weak and ridiculous as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> makes them, to an indifferent reader that shall compare them with the exceptions that he hath shaped unto them. Sharp Censures are but dull Answers.]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repl.</hi> I am not desirous to blast the reputation of that Learned man, if I were of any power to do it. But I confess his Doctrine in the matter of Justification I would have all friends of mine avoid; and I took it for my duty so to tell them: which I know not why you should be so offended at. I suppose you know how the Synod of <hi>Dort</hi> judged of his harsh language in another case, wherein he oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed <hi>Lubbertus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And seeing I am thus brought to take notice of the Witnesses that you produce as for your Cause; give me leave a little to review them.</p>
            <p>The first is Mr <hi>Pemble:</hi> But as Mr. <hi>Pemble</hi> is for you in his <hi>Vind. Grat.</hi> so when he came purposely to treat of that subject, it seems he changed his judgement: For in his <hi>Treat. of Justification,</hi> he saith as much of that as most of your adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: I pray you read him <hi>Pag.</hi> 15. <hi>c.</hi> 2. &amp; <hi>p.</hi> 22, 23, 24, 57. and then you will sure boast of M. <hi>Pemble</hi> no more: If he were once of your mind and afterward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected it, as he seems fully to have done, that is no great credit to it.</p>
            <p>Your second is Mr. <hi>Rutherford,</hi> who you say hath said as much as any of you. Wil you give the Reader leave to judge how far M. <hi>Rutherford</hi> was for you, by these words of his own, written after a fuller knowledge of the men of your Sect; In his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39618:15"/>
               <hi>Trial and Triumph of Faith,</hi> pag. 55. Serm. 8. he answers these Objections (against his first words, wherein he asserteth that [The condition of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is faith: Holiness and sanctification the Condition of the Covenants.) <hi>This do</hi> was the condition of the Covenant of Works; <hi>This Believe</hi> is the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Covenant.]</p>
            <p>[<hi>Object.</hi> 1. But some teach that this Covenant hath no Condition at all, so Dr. <hi>Crispe</hi> and other Libertines.] [<hi>Obj.</hi> 2. <hi>I will put my law in your inward parts,</hi> is no condition to be performed by us, but by God only.] [<hi>Obj.</hi> 4. Believing and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is but a consequent of the Covenant, not an Antecedent: so I must believe upon other grounds, but not in way of the condition of the Covenant, for in that tenor I am to do nothing.] [<hi>Obj.</hi> 5. The Covenant is Gods love to man to take him to himself, and that before the children do good or ill, and to him that work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth is the reward not reckoned of grace but of debt.] [<hi>Ob.</hi> 6. Our act of belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving is a work, and no work can be a condition of the Covenant of grace: yea Christ alone justifieth: Faith is not Christ, nor any partner with him in the work; yea we are justified before we believe, and faith only serveth for the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festation of Justification to our conscience, for we believe no lie, when we believe we are justified, but a truth; then it must be true, that we are justified before we believe.] These Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> answers as the Libertines Objections. It would be too tedious to recite his Answers, only some of that to the last I will recite.</p>
            <p>He saith, <hi>p.</hi> 59, 60, 61, 62. [Christ alone as the meritorious cause justifieth, and his imputed Righteousness as the formal cause: and this way Christ alone justifieth the Patriarchs, &amp;c. and all believers before they be born, but this is but the fountain ready to wash: but believe it Christ washeth not, while we be foul, &amp;c. nor is his name <hi>our Righteousness</hi> while we be sinners (<hi>i.e.</hi> unrenewed.) 1. Men not born cannot be the object of actual Righteousness; the unborn child needeth no actual application of Christs eye salve, gold, righteousness: Now Justificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is a real favour applied to us in time, just as Sanctification in the New birth, &amp;c. We cannot be justified before we believe. 1. We are damned before we believe, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. He that is justified is glorified, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. 3. We are born and by nature the sons of wrath, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2, 7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.5, 6. &amp; 6.14. 4. By faith we are only united to Christ, possessed of him, Christ dwelling in us, &amp;c. 5. This Justification without faith casteth loose the Covenant, <hi>I will be your God:</hi> But here's a condition, God is not bound and we free: Therefore this is the other part, <hi>Ye shall be my people.</hi> Now it is taught by Libertines, that there can be no closing with Christ in a promise that hath a qualification or condition expressed, and that conditional Promises are Legal, &amp;c. (Here he rejecteth Conditions, 1. In the Arminian sense, as they are the work of Free-will not acted by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determining grace of Christ. 2. In the Popish sense, as they are meritorious, as work of wages: and so I reiect them too.) 6. <hi>Paul</hi> in the Epistles to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> and <hi>Galatians,</hi> takes it for granted that Iustification is a work done in time, transient on us, not an immanent and eternal action, remaining either in God from eternity, or performed by Christ on the Cross before we believe, and so ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver taketh on him to prove that we are justified before we either do the works of the Law, or believe in Iesus Christ, but that we are Iustified by faith, &amp;c. and faith is not the naked Manifestation of our Iustification, so as we are Iustified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have faith: Satisfaction is indeed given to Iustice by Christ on the Cross, for all our sins before we believe, and before any justified person who lived this 1500 years was born; but, alas, that is not Iustification, but only the meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39618:16"/>cause of it: that is, as if one should say, This wall is white since the Creation of the world, though this very day only it was whited, because whiteness was in the world since the Creation.</p>
            <p>And that you may know the true nature of Justification, and Mr. <hi>Kendall</hi> and you may see what others say of the nature of the act as well as Mr. <hi>Woodbridge</hi> and I, mark the next words [Justification is a Forensical sentence in time pronounced <hi>in the Gospel,</hi> and applied to <hi>me Now,</hi> and never till the instant now, that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve: Its not formally an act of the understanding to know a truth concerning my self; But its an heart-adherence of the affections to Christ as the Saviour of sinners, at the presence of which a sentence of free absolution is pronounced: Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the Prince have it in his minde to pardon twenty malefactors; his grace is the cause why they are pardoned, yet are they never <hi>in Law</hi> pardoned, so as they can <hi>in Law</hi> plead immunity, till they can produce their Princes royal sealed pardon.] So Serm. 18. <hi>pag.</hi> 148. [Nay give me leave to say, that Antinomians make Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification and free grace their common place of Divinity, as if they onely had seen the visions of the Almighty and no other, but they are utterly ignorant thereof: For they confound and mix what the word distinguisheth, because <hi>Justification is onely a Removal of sin by a Law-way, so that in Law</hi> it cannot actually condemn.] So <hi>pag.</hi> 151. [Iustification freeth <hi>us in this life from all Law guilt and Obligation</hi> to wrath, which is but the second act of sin.] So <hi>pag.</hi> 153. [All which are true in a Law-sense, and in a Legal and Moral freedom from sin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] and [for they are in their actual guilt as touching the <hi>Law sting,</hi> and power, as no sins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> removed and taken away <hi>quoad actualem reatum eternae mortis,</hi> in their Law-demerit and guilt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is a Law removal of sin.] So oft <hi>pag.</hi> 154. <hi>&amp; passim:</hi> &amp; <hi>p.</hi> 162. speaking of Christs sufferings [This threefold taking away of sins I clear from Scripture. 1. Christ taketh away our sins on the Cross <hi>Causatively,</hi> and by way of merit, whileas he suffereth for our sins on the Cross. So <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.29. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. <hi>Isa.</hi> 53.10. Now this was the paying of a ransom for us, and a Legal translation of the eternal punishment of our sins, but it is not Iustifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor ever called Iustification: there is a sort of imputation of sin to Christ here, and a summe paid for me; but, with leave, No <hi>formall imputation,</hi> no foren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sical, and no personal Law-reckoning to me who am not yet born, far less cited before a Tribunal, and absolved from sin: When Christ had compleatly paid this summe, Christ was justified Legally, as a publique person, and all his seed <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentally, Meritoriously, Causatively,</hi> but not in their persons. There is a second removal of sin, when the believer is justified by faith This which is formally the Iustification of the believing sinner, the Believers person is Accepted, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, Iustified, and really translated by a <hi>Law change,</hi> from one state to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.]</p>
            <p>I have been the longer in reciting Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi>'s words, 1. Because of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves they suffice to confute your Opinion. 2. Because you so talk of [the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Divines and Churches,] and yet of those few that you produce for you, it may appear what they judge of your Cause. 3. That your allegations may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood hereafter by your Reader.</p>
            <p>Your third Dr. <hi>Twiss,</hi> and also <hi>Maccovius,</hi> I acknowledge are for you in the point now in question.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Parker</hi>'s words imply no more then <hi>Ratherfords, viz.</hi> That in Christs Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification we were justified <hi>causally;</hi> but that is a term of diminution, as to the formal Iustification; for till it be <hi>extra causas,</hi> It doth not exist: and it is an impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per use of the word justification.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:39618:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Chamier</hi> I have oft noted to have some passages that make for your Opinion: but that he contradicteth them elsewhere, I think is not hard to manifest. I will not deny the truth for the credit of the man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calvin</hi> is so express and frequent against you, as few men more. I came but now from citing some passages to that end against <hi>Ludiomaeus Colvinus,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will not now lose time in doing it again, when all men that will reade his Books, may quickly finde that he was no friend to the Justification of Infidels. I marvell rather that you had not cited <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> who indeed is blamed for leaning that way, and called <hi>Seneca</hi> by such a Christian name unless perhaps he was deceived by <hi>Hierome,</hi> as <hi>Hierome</hi> was by his counterfeit Epistle, and thought <hi>Seneca</hi> a believer indeed) And you might have alleadged an inclination in <hi>Erasmus</hi> for you, who could scarce forbear saying, <hi>Sancte Socrates ora pro nobis. Calvin</hi>'s words mean but this much (which you cite) that seeing God offereth Remission, and we do but Accept it by faith, therefore God doing his part in offering it, he saith that <hi>respectu Dei Justificatio fidem praecedit,</hi> though we are not actually justified till after. For that offer is common to Infidels. In that very discourse <hi>Calvin</hi> hath many passages against you: As <hi>pag (mihi fol.)</hi> 390. <hi>Nos autem meminerimus fidei na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam à Christo aestimandam esse: quia quod nobis offert Deus in Christo, non nisi fide recipimus. Proinde quicquid nobis est Christus id ad fidem transfertur, quae nos com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potes &amp; Christi &amp; omntum ejus bonorum sacit. Ne{que} aliter verum esset illud Johannis, fidem nostram esse victoriam, qua mundus vincitur, nisi nos in Christum insereret qui solus est mundi victor.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zanchy</hi> in the words cited by you useth inconvenient expressions; but that he is fully against you, is manifest in many places of his Writing. But I have newly Vindicated <hi>Zanchy</hi> from <hi>Ludiomaeus Colvinus,</hi> who urgeth the same words as you do.</p>
            <p>So I have done <hi>Alstedius</hi> too, and therefore shall say no more of him.</p>
            <p>So also have I vindicated <hi>Amesius</hi> against the same <hi>Colvinus:</hi> and as for this te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony which you adde more then he, <hi>viz. ex Antisynodal.</hi> p. 164. his <hi>[atiquo modo] in favorem restituti,</hi> by which he there expoundeth reconciliation, is so stretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a word, as may well be yielded true: for it will let in as improper a reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as yours: but yet <hi>Amesius</hi> will not use the word Justification so improperly, at least without discovering the impropriety.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <head>§. 3.</head>
            <p>THe next bout that you have with me, is <hi>pag.</hi> 25. when you have done with Mr. <hi>Burgess.</hi> And you there fall on to some purpole, thus:
<q>[Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s character of an Antinomian will bring all our Protestant Writers under this censure.]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repl.</hi> Still more falshood! Is the ninth Commandment blotted out of your Decalogue, as the second out of the Papists? Or think you that you are under no Law; or that God sees no iniquity in you, so as to hate it?</p>
            <p>But let's hear your proof.
<q>[For with him they are Antinomians who hold (1.) That our Evangelical Righteousness is without us in Christ, or performed by him and not by our selves]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repl.</hi> Here are more uncruths then one in these words also, 1. I never said that they who denied this were Autinomians, but that it was a piece of Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39618:17"/>doctrine, and that the Antinomians did deny it: Nay lest any should think that I accounted all Antinomians that are offended at this; I added [and some that are no Antinomians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 109] I call not all Antinomians that hold any one of their doctrines. 2. It is untrue that all our Protestant Writers are against this, (as I have fully shewed elsewhere) yea or any one accounted Orthodox that ever I met with, as to the sense of my words: For though some of them will not allow the name of <hi>Righteousness</hi> to our faith and obedience (though the Scripture useth it twenty and twenty times I think) and others commonly will call it Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, but will not say that we are righteous or justified by it. (A strange Righteousness that doth not make righteous <hi>formaliter,</hi> as it is a strange existent whiteness, that makes no man white, and a strange honesty or goodness, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, that makes no man honest good or noble:) yet do all the Protestants that ever I met with yield to my explicatory Proposition, which I purposely annexed, that none might mistake me and quarrell about words, <hi>viz.</hi> [I hough Christ per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the conditions of the Law and satisfied for our <hi>non</hi> performance, yet it is our selves that must perform the conditions of the Gospel,] <hi>i. e.</hi> by the grace of God. Who deny this but your own Sect, and a few Divines, that in that point joyn with you in making the New Covenant to have no Condition: who are but very few indeed comparatively. Nay of the very Libertines, the first that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that taught men when they doubted of the truth of their faith or repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to comfort themselves with this perswasion, that Christ hath believed and repented for them, was <hi>Saltmarsh;</hi> against whom Mr. <hi>Gataker</hi> hath told you more truth then I perceive you are willing to learn. 3. Here is added to these open untruths a secret calumny: For you deliver it in general terms, as if I did hold that which Divines commonly call our Evangelicall Righteousness to be in our selves and not in Christ. When as I purposely explained my self, to avoid all strife about words, that as Christs Righteousness is called Evangelical, because the Gospel revealeth and giveth it; so our righteousness Evangelical is without us. This you hide, to make the Reader that seeth but your words, to think that I hold some monstrous thing. Be it known therefore to you and all men, That I trust on that Righteousness of Christ which is without me Materially, and formally consisteth in <hi>my Right to Impunity and to the Kingdom of Glory;</hi> and that I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no righteousness within me consisting in faith, repentance or obedience, but onely A particular Righteousness required by the new Covenant in meer subordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Christs Righteousness, as the condition on which it is made ours; which is first in order of nature a meer condition of our full righteousness in Christ, and then secondarily a particular Righteousness it self, when the Cause comes to trial, Whether we did perform that condition or not? If you do not understand these fews words, I intreate you either to study them till you do, or else forbear any more to reproach that which you understand not: and do not intimate me to be an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidel, in denying Christs Righteousness.</p>
            <p>You proceed,
<q>[Or (2.) that Justification is a free act of God without any condition on our part for the obtaining of it.]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> This is in sense the same with the former. Here also is more untruths then one intimated or expressed (I confess they fall so thick from you, that I doubt I shall be thought a railer by your party, and too sharp by others, for numbring them to you, and desiring you to repent.) 1. I onely said that [the Antimonians think grace cannot be free if there be any condition on our part for enjoying it.] But doth it follow, that because I say, [the Antinomians say so] that therefore I
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39618:17"/>say [they are Antinomians who do say so.] The Papists say, Episcopacy is a superiour order to Presbyterie: but [they are not therefore Papists that shall so say, unless there be somewhat else so to denominate them.] 2. Do not all the Learned men into whose hands your Book shall fall, know that it is false, that the Protestants do hold the opinion which I here call Antinomian? Do not the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessions of the Churches, and the generality of Divines make faith the condition of the Covenant, and yet maintain it to be free? If you will speak untruths hereafter, for your credit sake, do it more modestly and warily, and open not your shame in the sight of the world. It were no great wisdom in me on this occasion to heap up the Testimonies of Churches and Divines, in a case so well known.</p>
            <p>You adde,
<q>[Or else (3.) that Justification is an immanent act, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently from eternity, which was the judgement of <hi>Alsted, Pemble, Twiss, Rutherford,</hi> &amp;c.]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> I think there are at least two untruths and a half here too. 1. Whether it were <hi>Rutherford</hi>'s judgement, let the Reader judge by what is written out of him before. 2. Of <hi>Alsted</hi> I speak as afore I said against <hi>Colvinus.</hi> 3. It is half true of <hi>Pemble,</hi> in that he was once of that opinion, and but half true, because in his Treat. of <hi>Iustification</hi> he fully asserteth ours. 4. What are these four men to all the Protestant Writers which you affirmed I would bring under this cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure?</p>
            <p>You adde,
<q>[Or (4.) that we must not perform duty for life and salvation, but from life and salvation: or that we must not make the attaning of Justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or salvation the end of our endeavours, but obey in Thankfulness, and because we are justified and saved. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. In the place quoted page 14. is no such thing in any of the four Editions of that Book. But I well remember the sense of most of it about p. 10. or 11. and that I largely prove it in the Appendix of my <hi>Aphor.</hi> 2. But indeed dare you say, that all (or any) Protestant Writers do hold this Point? Now God forbid! If they did, I profess seriously I would scarce be called a Protestant, if they held but that one Error alone. Did not you know in this Point, that not onely Learned men, but the ordinary sort of Christians can disprove you? I appeal to all honest men, women and children of understanding, that use to reade <hi>Dod, Bolton, Perkins, Preston, Hooker, Rogers, Wheatly,</hi> &amp;c. What say you Sirs? Do these Writers teach you that you must use no endeavours for your salvation? that you must do nothing for eternal life? Nay do they teach you that the very unregenerate must do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to obtain the life of grace? 3. Truly I hoped well in the beginning that you had not been neer so far gone your self, as to own this desperate opinion. The Lord keep you from practising it, or, I think, you are a lost man. 4. Yet let me tell you, that I further believe, 1. That thankfulness and Love should be the chiefest spring of duty 2. Yea even with the unregenerate, our first labour should be when we have convinced them of sin and misery, and the truth of the Gospel, to possess them with thanks and love for that common redemption, which I suppose you deny; I mean there is matter in Christs common love in his satisfaction, for us to plead with sinners for gratitude (before assurance of special love) though they have no hearts to perceive it to purepose, till God open their hearts by his Spirit: 3. The principle of our new spiritual life is it that Christians must act from, in their whole course. Thus far I say we must act from life and love. 4. And also, from Gods love antecedent to ours.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:39618:18"/>
            <p> You conclude, <hi>Now let any man who is moderately versed in our Protestant Writers but speak on whom this Arrow falls: I might instance in many others, but I will not put the Reader to so much trouble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Now let any man who hath read the ninth Commandment, and the words of Christ, <hi>By their fruits ye shall know them,</hi> judge. 1. Whether it be not his duty to lament the sinful state of this Brother, and to pray God to forgive him (though I know not whether he will pray so for himself.) 2. And to pitty poor Christians that shall hear and reade the confident words of such men, and have not means to discern their vanity. 3. And judge whether that be not a bad opinion that can entangle even a godly man in such a course of sin: And whether we ought not all to take heed of believing that we are justified before we were born, or that we ought to do nothing for our own salvation; or that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don is given without any condition, so much as Acceptance. For my part I impute these faults to the Opinion first, and to the man but as from thence. And it may be Gods will to permit him to practice according to the tendency of his doctrine, even in the Book wherein he maintaineth it, that those that cannot understand his errors in themselves, may <hi>see</hi> them in their effects.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="section">
            <head>§. 4.</head>
            <p>THe next bout that you have with me, you begin thus, <hi>pag.</hi> 29. <hi>He may if be will compare his doctrine with Mr.</hi> Baxter's <hi>notions (whom Mr.</hi> W. <hi>follows at the very heels)</hi> Thes. 56.26.73, <hi>&amp;c. in his</hi> Aph. <hi>who denies, That Christs obedience is the material, the imputation of his Righteousness the formall cause of our Iustification, or that saith is the instrument by which we do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> What an unhappy name is mine to your mouth, that is seldom mentioned without sin! 1. I did not deny Christs obedience to be the material cause in the sense as Divines commonly so called it; and therefore not absolutely &amp; without explication, as you recite it: But 1. As matter is proper to substance, so justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication being an accident hath no matter. Are not you of the same minde? 2. As accidents do inhere in the subject, so the subject is commonly called their matter: In this sense too our Righteousness or Justification paflive is not in Christs Righteousness, but in our selves, and so our selves are the matter: for I think it is we that are justified Nor do I believe yet that it is one act whereby Christ and we are justified. There is then no other proper matter of our Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication (the later being not properly so called it self.) 3. But yet as our Divines commonly call Christs Righteousness of satisfaction the matter of ours, because it is the matter that merited it, so am I well content to do, and so I willingly profess that our righteousness is materially out of us, in Christs satisfaction: and therefore I there said that they speak nearer the matter that call it [the matter of our righteousness] then they that call it the matter of our active Iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Your next charge is, that I deny Imputation to be the form. 1. I both grant it and deny it, as you understand the words. I did in that place take the word Imputation in one onely sense, for Donation, and so said, it was rather in order of nature before Justification, <hi>i. e.</hi> sentential: and so saith many other. 2. But I would defire you and all men to take notice that those two pag. 218, 219.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39618:18"/>I have much altered, as finding the expressions unfit, and therefore do revoke them. And I say 1. That imputation is taken either for Donation or Adjudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and that mental, by meer estimation, or Judicial by sentence. 2. That Justification is Constitutive, or Sentential. And so I judge 1. That imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Christs Righteousness taken for Donation is the form of constitutive Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification (Active Donation of Active Justification, and Passive Donation of Passive Justification.) 2. That sentential adjudication of Christs Righteousness to us, is the form of our sentential Justification. 3. And that after the manner of men, or by extrinsick denomination <hi>à novitate objecti,</hi> it may be said, that God doth impute righteousness to us by mental estimation or acceptation, or appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, when he looks on us as then Righteous and not before, and therefore may be said then to begin so to esteem, accept or approve us, because before there was no object for an act of such denomination. And this may be called the form of a mental Justification. So in all three senses I say that Imputation is the form of Justification, but not one sort of Imputation the form of another sort of Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; which was all that I there meant to deny, but unfitly expressed my mind, as in some other places of that Book, for which I have ever since sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How far I deny faith to be the instrument, I refer the Reader to my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to Mr. <hi>Blake</hi> and Mr. <hi>Kendall.</hi> You a little after could say, You thought I ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued rationally in that when it fitted your turn.</p>
            <p>You add, <hi>He plainly ascribes the same kind of Causality to Christ and faith, making them to differ,</hi> Only secundum magis &amp; minus, <hi>that Christ is the</hi> sine qua non prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalis, <hi>and faith the</hi> sine qua non minus principalis.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. More calumny and untruth. 1. I said <hi>[Christs satissaction,]</hi> you say <hi>Christ:</hi> as if Christ caused no other way but by satisfaction. 2. The word <hi>[Only]</hi> is your notorious forgery. 3. I did in the same place expresly say that Christs satisfaction is the Meritorious cause, and <hi>sine qua non,</hi> in several respects. 4. It was only in <hi>sensu physico</hi> that I called it <hi>causa sine qua non</hi> (and so do your best friends, in sense) but a moral cause, yea of highest dignity I asserted it to be. 5. I affirmed that faith was no moral cause at all. And now let the Reader judge of your Veracity, and whether you recite not my words just as, you know who, is commonly said to have cited Scripture to Christ.</p>
            <p>You adjoyn in a Parenthesis, <hi>[He might have listed sin in the same rank, which too, is a</hi> sine qua non <hi>of our Justification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. Every thing <hi>sine qua non res existet,</hi> is not <hi>Causa sine qua non.</hi> Though this have no true causality, yet it is a <hi>medium ad finem,</hi> and hath a tendency to the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, by which it doth so far emulate causality, that it receiveth the nature. But who ever called privation <hi>Causam sine qua non?</hi> and yet it is <hi>Principium sine quo non.</hi> Sin in being is the true cause of guilt: and guilt is the <hi>materia removenda,</hi> or the <hi>Terminus à quo</hi> of Justification, it being the very thing that Remission doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy: even as life doth death, or light darkness. 2. What if you had spoke sense in this? yet what had it been to the strengthning of your accusation? Would you have your Reader believe that I make sin to be the meritorious cause of our Justification, or to have that Dignity in moral causation which I ascribed to the satisfaction of Christ?</p>
            <p>Next you say, <hi>That faith and works in a larger sense are meritorious causes of life and blessedness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Another false witness: I mentioned merit in a larger improper sense: (as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:39618:19"/>all Divines that ever I read against the Papists on that Point do) but never called them <hi>a Meritorious cause</hi> that I know of. Why would you print such things which you knew might be discovered? It may be you will say, It is all one. I answer, 1. You should then have said that I speak to that sense, and not that I speak <hi>so:</hi> Nay you should have put down my own words, and left the Reader to judge of the sense, and not put your own sense on them, and then say, I speak so. 2. It is not all one. For in denying them to be properly Merit, I deny them to be any way causing by that Merit: therefore you feign me to yield to a further impropriety then I did, or else to false doctrine. 3. But will you go tell the world what is my judgement, because I take the word <hi>Merit</hi> in the Fathers in a larger improper sense? Christ called <hi>Peter</hi> Satan, for his carnal counsel: Will you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine thence that Christ judged <hi>Peter</hi> to be the Devil? <hi>David</hi> was <hi>a worm and no man</hi> in improper sense: Must he needs be lasht by you for speaking false do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in so saying? Will you accuse Christ of Error for saying, He is the Vine, and his Father the Husbandman? He is the Way, the Door, the Shepherd, &amp;c? The word <hi>Reward</hi> is oft enough used in Scripture, and so is the word <hi>[Worthy:]</hi> and yet you conclude they are both used improperly: And will you therefore say that Christ was a Papist, or Socinian, or Erroneous, for using those words im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly? Having spoken so much to your Head, let me say this to your Heart: Brother, you engaged your self in Baptism to fight against the Devil: your life is or should be a continual combat against him: How comes it to pass then that you have so learned his accusing art, when you should have learned of Christ to be <hi>holy,</hi> and to <hi>love your brother,</hi> and to <hi>speak the truth?</hi> I do seriously advise you to repent of these ways, and to be think you whether your opinions encourage you not hereto. If you reject this wholsom advice, take heed that it rise not up against you in judgement, and if you proceed in such courses impenitently, take heed lest those sins prove unpardoned hereafter, which you say were pardoned before you believed, or repented, or were born. Because I desire it may not be so, therefore do I wran you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 30. you say, <hi>Too many of our Protestants (setting aside the word Merit, which yet Mr.</hi> B. <hi>thinks may be admitted) do tread directly in their steps; they ascribe as much to works as Papists do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. It seems then other Protestants are as much Papists herein as I, in sense, though not in word. 2. Another slander you are guilty of (I say Guilty, for all you say its pardoned before committed.) Did ever I say <hi>The word Merit may be admitted.</hi> Shew where if you can. I said indeed that in that large improper sense, <hi>Works may be called Merits,</hi> thereby intending no <hi>Moral admission</hi> of it: but only a <hi>capacity in the term,</hi> to signifie such a thing by improper use. But I never said that it is no sin in them that do use words so improperly, or that <hi>it may be admitted.</hi> For my part, I think the danger is so great, that the very use of the word is to be avoided by us, except in interpretations of others, or with them that will use it whether we will or not; and so we must speak to men in their own lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage sometime, or say nothing. 3. Better men then you or I, have used the word Merit, even the Church of Christ, the Councils and Fathers for 1400 years and more: And <hi>Austin</hi> that most eminently vindicated the glory of free grace, yet never disused this word himself. If I have sinned therefore but as all the Church hath done so long, and in its spring, I hope I am no Papist. 4. I would again have you and all men take notice how these overdoing men are the greatest Undoers. How could this man credit Popery more almost then he doth? As bad
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:39618:19"/>as I am (which is bad I confess) yet if he could make all my neighbours believe that Papists be such as I, he would do more to make them Papists, then such ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guings as this Book contains would undo. And I think some R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lers that now may be in the mind to deny Papists the liberty of their Religion, or at least of preaching to others, would grant them both, if they thought that the Religion of Papists were no worse then mine? So the argument would run thus; <hi>R.B.</hi> is a Papist: But he should have liberty: Therefore Papists should have liberty. But yet this is not that I aim at: But that he should place Popery in a thing which the Church hath used for so many hundred years, even as high as any Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astical History or Writing can give us light, is not this the way to make all turn Papists, and say, Hath Christ had no Church but Papists so long? then we will be Papists too: For sure the Head had still a Body. Well, when God will heal his Churches divisions, he will teach men moderation.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="section">
            <head>§. 5.</head>
            <p>THe next assault I meet with, is <hi>pag.</hi> 50, 51. §. 5. <hi>Some of our late Divines (who seem to disclaim the doctrine of the Papists and Arminians) say the very same; who explain themselves to this effect. That faith doth Justifie as a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, or Antecedent qualification, by which we are made capable of being Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified, according to the order and Constitution of God: The sulfilling of which Condition say they is our Evangelical Righteousness, whereby we are Justified in the sight of God. Mr.</hi> Baxter <hi>is so fond of this notion, that although in one place he finds fault with the length of our Creeds and Confessions, yet he would have this made an Article of the Creed, a part of our Childrens Catechisms, and to be believed by every man that is a Christian, so apt are we to smile upon our own babes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> More of the old language still: 1. Is this <hi>the very same</hi> as the Papists and Arminians hold, which you say it is the <hi>very same</hi> with, viz. <hi>That God for Christs sake accounts our imperfect saith, to be perfect Righteousness? You know</hi> they <hi>take not</hi> perfect Righteousness <hi>for Righteousness only that hath a formal Metaphysical perfection of Entity as I do. You say</hi> Their opinion is, that God in the Covenant of Grace requires saith, which in his gracious Acceptation stands in stead of that obedience to the Moral Law which we ought to perform. <hi>But I say that Christs satisfaction is instead of that obedience, in that it is instead of our suffering for disobedience. You credit the Papists and Arminians still, if you can prove that their opinion is the very same with this. Do they renounce Merit? and do not our Divines generally make that the point of our difference about Justification by Works?</hi> viz. <hi>Whether the merit of Good Works Justifie? which I heartily and constantly deny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I have told you before, that I say, that we are no otherwise Justified by the Evangelical Righteousness in question, then in necessary subordination to Christs own Righteousness, as the Condition of our Legal title to it, of his own appointing. This you conceal.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is another fiction, that it is this <hi>Notion</hi> that I would have an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Creed (if you mean the <hi>Notiones secundae,</hi> yea or the <hi>primae</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly.) For I told you that I spoke of the Matter and not the phrase: It is the substance of the doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi> That we must <hi>believe</hi> our selves, and not think
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39618:20"/>we may be excused, as having a Saviour that hath believed in himself for us.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For my part as I am confident it is implied in the Creed, so it shall be my Creed while I breath, by the grace of God. And I think Christ put it into the Creed if ever he made a Creed: sure it is the summ or principal heads of the Gospel which he sent his Disciples to preach to the world, and I think that is part of the Creed: and what that was is evident, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16. <hi>He that Believeth and is baptized shall be saved, and he that believeth not shall be damned.</hi> And it was the Creed that was taught them before baptism: and that was, <hi>Repent and believe for remission of sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You add, <hi>Though I honor Mr.</hi> Baxter <hi>for his excellent parts, yet I must suspend my Assent to his new Creed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. No newer then the Scripture, nay elder then Scripture, for it is as old as the Covenant of Grace. 2. I had rather be without your Honor, then you should be without the Truth: not that I much care whether you be of my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, as such; but that I care for your salvation. But my hope is, that though you take not faith to be a Condition of Salvation, yet you do Believe on other Grounds; and if you have that which is the condition, I doubt not but you may be saved, though you know it not to be the condition: And if you think you may not Endeavor for salvation, yet if you <hi>do endeavor it,</hi> and <hi>act for it</hi> while you say the contrary that it may not be done, I doubt not of your safety, because you hold that Practically which you deny speculatively. But I must tell you, that he that thinks, though but speculatively, that he <hi>ought not to do it,</hi> is in great danger of being drawn to omit it.</p>
            <p>You proceed, <hi>I shall prove anon that faith is not said to Justifie as an Antecedent Condition, which qualifies us for Justification: but at present I shall only render him the reasons of my disbelief, why I cannot look upon faith as that Evangelical Righteousness, by which we are Justified. I shall not insist upon it, though it be not altogether unconsiderable, that this notion is Guilty of too much confederacy with the forenamed enemies of the Christian faith: For though it is no good argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to say, that Papists, Socinians,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>do hold this or that, therefore it is not true; yet it will follow that such and such Tenets have been held by Papists, &amp;c. and unanimously opposed by our Protestant writers; therefore they ought to be the more suspected, and especially such tenets of theirs, as have been the chief points in difference between us and them, as this is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. I shall as readily suspect such points as bear your description, as you. 2. It is untrue that this is such, <hi>quoad terminos,</hi> much more <hi>quoad sensum.</hi> All our Divines maintain an Inherent Righteousness, and in the same sense as they (so far as I understand them of chief note) do deny them to justifie us, I deny it too.</p>
            <p>You add, <hi>Our Brethren that have started this Notion, do take faith as the others do, in a proper sense, they attribute as much to the</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> credere, <hi>as</hi> Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, Arminius, <hi>or any other. Faith it self (saith Mr.</hi> B.) <hi>is our Righteousness: There was never any Papist so absurd as to say, that our Faith, Love, &amp;c. are perfect legal Righteousness; but that God</hi> judicio misericordiae, non justitiae, <hi>doth account and accept of it instead of perfect righteousness. For my part I must confess that I can see no difference between them but in expressions. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists do acknowledge the satisfaction of Christ, and that he is the meritorious Cause of our Justification. They say indeed that we are not Justified by the Righteousness of Christ Imputed, but by a Righteousness inherent in us, or
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39618:20"/>righteous actions performed by us. And what do our Brethren say less then this? But I shall follow this parallel no further.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. What do they say less then this, who maintain Imputed Righteousness, <hi>viz.</hi> less then those that deny it? I'le put another question upon this of yours: Whether a Question can be false? A Logician will say, It cannot be false; and yet a Divine will say, It may be <hi>mendacium;</hi> and yet both say true: Is not that strange! 2. I desire the Reader to excuse me from the trouble of enumerating all the untruths in these lines (for I am aweary of that work, and its to little pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit,) and to expect my full satisfaction to this Parallel, in my Reply to Mr. <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> (if God will,) where I shall shew him whether I be a Papist or an Arminian; and whether his tongue and his brothers be any slander.</p>
            <p>You proceed §. 6. <hi>The Reasons which turn the scales of my judgement against this Notion, that our faith or faithful actions, are that Evangelicall Righteousness, by which we are justified, Are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Before I weigh your Reasons, I will do the Reader that favour which you deny him, <hi>viz.</hi> To let him know a little better the state of the Question, and what it is that I maintain.</p>
            <p>Understand therefore Reader, that I hold these conclusions (which I shall fullier open, God willing, in Reply to Mr. <hi>Crandon.</hi>) 1. That Gods universal Law of Nature requireth of us perfect Obedience, on Pain of eternall death if we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it not. 2. We all sinned, and so were liable to that Death. 3. Christ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Mediator, and stept between us and the ful execution, and took the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty upon himself, and be came a sacrifice to offended Justice, and a Ransom for the sinners. 4. Upon this he acquired <hi>Novum Jus Dominii &amp; Novum Jus Imperii</hi> over all men; being now the Soveraign of the world as Redeemer, as superadded to the former Dominion and Soveraignty which the Father, Son and holy Ghost had as Creator. 5. As Christ the Anointed and Soveraign Redeemer, he made <hi>Legom Remediantem,</hi> An Act of Oblivion, A new Law, <hi>viz.</hi> A Law of Grace; thereby granting free pardon, Justification, Adoption, and right to Glory to all that will sincerely Repent and Believe in him; and Peremptorily Concluding those to everlasting death that will not. 6. This Repenting and Believing is nothing but Assenting so heartily to the Truth of the Gospel, as thereupon to accept the Lord Jesus Christ and life in him, as he is offered, <hi>viz.</hi> As a pardoner by Grateful Consent and Confidence, as Good to us, by Love; as Soveraign, by giving up our selves to him for guidance, and to take him for the Physitian of our souls, to rest on him, and apply his sharpest plaisters, and take his bitterest medicines, and which are most ungrateful to flesh and blood (and not to be lieve that the cure is done already:) and, as a <hi>free gift</hi> we must accept this Grace, with confession of our own utter undeserving, and our desert of eternal wrath, and therefore with <hi>Repentance</hi> to the glory of him that <hi>freely</hi> saveth us: and lastly, as he is the Purchaser, Giver, and Conductor to the <hi>unseen</hi> everlasting glory, which is the great End for which we do receive him; without respect to which End, saith were no saving faith. 6. Remission and Justification by Christs Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Merit, being given us by a New Law, which hath its Precepts and Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we are obliged by this Law to perform these Conditions, and shall be judged by this Law, whether we have performed them or no. In which judgment, he that is accused not to have performed them, <hi>i.e.</hi> to be an unbeliever and rebel against the Lord Redeemer, must plead his own actual performance, and deny the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation. And therefore that performance is the <hi>Justitia Causae,</hi> the righteousness of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39618:21"/>that his cause, and of his person so far. 7. In respect to this personal New Covenant righteousness, the Scripture doth twenty times, if not twenty more, call men righteous: yea even in the description of the Iudgement, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. last. 8. As this new Law is but <hi>Lex particularis Remedians,</hi> properly subordinate to the Law of Nature, so this personal righteousness, is not our <hi>Justitia universalis,</hi> but a particular righteousness, subordinate to the righteousness of the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus. 9. There being therefore a twofold Iustification or righteousness, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal and subordinate, one which answers the Law of nature, the other which answers the false charge of not performing the condition of the Law of Grace; one in Christs Satisfaction and Merit, the other in our faith and repentance; one consisting in the Pardon of all our sin and the right to Impunity and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the other in our having the true condition of pardon and right; It follows, that when the question is of Justification in the first sense, and of the matter (as we call it) of that Iustification, <hi>i. e.</hi> the thing for which we are justified merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously, that we must then conclude that it is onely Christs righteousness that is our Iustification or our righteousness; and that faith or repentance is not the least part of it: But if the Question be only of the meer subordinate righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and Iustification, then we must say that our own faith and repentance, &amp; not Christs satisfaction is that righteousness: For it is a debasing of Christs righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, to bring it so low; and it is no other exalting of faith then God hath in his Covenant exalted it, to raise it so high, as to be thus subordinate to Christs righteousness, that it may become ours. 10. In regard of the first great Iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of a sinner, consisting in remission of sin <hi>(constitutive)</hi> and sentential absolving him from guilt, Faith or any work of mans is but the condition <hi>sine qua non,</hi> and not the least part of that righteousness (as is said.) But in regard of that subordinate Iustification which is but a means to the former, faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance are our righteousness it self, so that faith is first in order of nature but a condition; but secondarily, when the case at Iudgements, Whether we have performed that condition or not, then consequentially it is our subordinate par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Righteousness. 11. No man can perform this condition without Gods special grace. 12. It was the intent and absolute Will, yea and undertaking of Christ dying, to cause all the Elect of God infallibly to perform this condition. Thus Reader I have anticipated some part of what I intended to say in my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to Mr. <hi>Crandon,</hi> as being unwilling to delay thy information, or be guilty of the continuance of thy prejudice against the truth. I confess I have lately recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Animadversions from Learned men, against the thing here laid down, <hi>viz</hi> a personal Righteousness; but Gods Word is so plain, and mens reasons against it in my eyes so weak, that I am more then ever confirmed in it. I equally hate vain distinction and confusion: But to distinguish between the Law of nature &amp; the Law of grace, between Christs Righteousness imputed, and the condition of Imputation, and so between our primary Righteousness &amp; our subordinate Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, I think are no vain distinctions. Let's make it plain by a similitude. In a time of Rebellion, upon the Princes intercession and satisfaction, An Act of grace is granted, that whoever will acknowledge the Princes favour and the Kings, and Accept a pardon, shall be forgiven, and shall not die. Is it not one thing here to accuse a man as a Traytor, and another thing to accuse him of not accepting the pardon? and are not these two causes referring to two Laws? yet one subordinate to the other, and not coordinate. When he is accused of Treason, he is justified by the Act of Grace: and this is his <hi>Titulus ad Liberationem.</hi> But
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39618:21"/>when it is but one Traytor of many that accepteth the Act of Grace, and he is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused of <hi>non</hi>-acceptance, and the case to be decided falls to be this. Whether the Act of Grace give that man any Right to impunity? then because it was a conditional Act, he must be here justified by pleading that he did perform the condition. And so that justification which is but subordinate, and in order of dignity but secondary, as a means to the former, is yet in order of Plea at Judgement to go before it, as the means must be before the end.</p>
            <p>If thou be unprejudiced, Reader, and lovest the truth, I should think that I need not say much to Mr. <hi>Eyres</hi> Arguments, having given thee in these Conclusions, so clear a ground of answering them all; But I shall briefly take an account of them, and so return to Mr. <hi>Eyre:</hi> Who thus begins.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>If we are not justified by our own works, then our believing, &amp;c. is not that Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical righteousness by which we are justified: But we are not Justified by our own works: Therefore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Distinguish of works, and distinguish of justifying. 1. That Iustificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which consisteth in Remission of sin, is not in our own faith; but that which consisteth in performing the condition of Remission is. 2. Works are taken either as <hi>Paul</hi> doth (which he describeth <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Which make the Reward to be not of grace but of debt:</hi> Or as <hi>James</hi> doth, in necessary subordination to Christ. In the former sense I deny your consequence; In the later sense I deny your <hi>minor</hi> or Antecedent. And if you say that <hi>Paul</hi> supposeth that all works do make the reward to be of debt; I answer, 1. Then <hi>James</hi> saith we are justified by impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, or by unlawfull ways. The works that <hi>James</hi> mentions are possible and lawfull: works that make the reward to be of debt are impossible, and the attempt of such unlawfull: Therefore there are some works which do not make the reward to be of debt. 2. The same <hi>Paul</hi> that saith we are justified by Christ, saith oft enough that we are justified by faith, and that faith is and shall be imputed to us for Righteousness.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Paul</hi> takes works for Meritorious actions deserving wages. Faith is no such work; therefore on that ground still I deny your consequence.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You must distinguish of the word <hi>[by]</hi> when you say, We are, or are not ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified <hi>by</hi> faith. Its one thing to be justified <hi>by</hi> faith, as the matter of our Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness. So we deny it, as to our great principal Iustification. And its another thing to be justified <hi>by</hi> faith as a meerly subordinate condition <hi>sine qua non:</hi> and so <hi>Paul</hi> still includeth it as plain as a man can speak. Still saying, We are justified by faith. This answers fully the Texts cited by you: and is another answer then that of the Papists to which you here Reply. Yet to your answers to the last, (that <hi>Others say, It is not works of the Law, but Gospel.</hi>) I must give you these brief Notes (supposing that the words you answer are none of mine till better explained, limited and reformed.)</p>
            <p>To your first, I say, <hi>distinguit Lex. Paul</hi> and <hi>James</hi> else will hardly be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled. Yea <hi>Paul</hi> himself distinguisheth, by punctual expressing the works of the Law, or telling you he means only works that make <hi>the reward to be not of grace but of debt;</hi> and taking in faith as that by which we are justified.</p>
            <p>To your second, you speak very darkly and dangerously: and against you I return. If <hi>Paul</hi> exclude all Debt which follows upon promise, then he excludes all that follows upon an absolute promise, as well as upon a conditional: But the Consequent is false, therefore so is the Antecedent. The reason of the Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is clear. Either you mean that this is <hi>from the promise, as a promise,</hi> or
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:39618:22"/>else <hi>from the promise as conditional.</hi> If the former, then it follows an absolute promise as much as a conditional; and then you must deny all Gods promises, and then you will be against the Gospel indeed. If the later, then I say, That the promise <hi>qua</hi> conditional, gives no right; distinguish of conditions: Some are of such value as to be Meritorious: these cause the debt by Merit: Others have no meriting value (as the acceptance of a free gift:) these are no causes so much as Moral, but meer conditions. And whoever knows what a condition in Law-sense is, knows that as such, it only suspends the act of a Testament or other gift, till it be performed, but doth not cause it, when it is performed.</p>
            <p>To your third, it is answered already.</p>
            <p>To your fourth, see my answer to Mr <hi>Blake.</hi> Also, The Gospel is a subordinate Law, and the matter of its precept is taken out of the general Law of nature: but informed with a new promise. <hi>Adams</hi> body was earth; but yet to be distinguish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from common earth, and worthy of another name, when it was informed with a new from, even his soul. I doubt you will not apprehend well what these short expressions contain, unless you will please to consider and digest them.</p>
            <p>To your fifth <hi>Paulus Burgensis,</hi> a Christian Iew, on <hi>Jam. add. ad</hi> Lyrani <hi>Annot.</hi> tels us that his Countreymens opinion was, that God denominated a man righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or wicked according to the greater part of his works. If he had more good works then bad, he was righteous: else not. The Iews did not think to be justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by perfect unsinning obedience: for they were to confess sin, and sacrifice for it. But they thought that their sacrifices themselves and their good works might so procure the pardon of their sins, or prevail against their evil works, that they looked not for Righteousness to Christ the end of the Law. This is the justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by works which <hi>Paul</hi> argues against directly; and only consequentially <hi>à fortiore</hi> we may gather it, as of perfect obedience, which is to us impossible, as it may be supposed to justifie us from the charge <hi>of being sinners.</hi> Yet because their obedience was not perfect, <hi>Paul</hi> might well convince them that it could not justifie when they erred in thinking, that imperfect obedience, by the help of sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, might justifie.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Your second Argument is this, 2. <hi>If the righteousness whereby we are Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified be a perfect Righteousness, then we are not Justified by our obedience to Gospel-precepts: But,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Therefore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is answered in the former, by the same distinctions. The righteousness whereby we are justified as <hi>by the Matter, or Meritorious cause,</hi> is perfect: and therefore faith or obedience is not such. But the righteousness whereby we are justified as a meer condition, and consequentially a righteousness subordinate to the former, is not perfect; and therefore of this your consequence fails. All your following words therefore to this, are meerly beside the Point, and vain. I never doubted of that, Whether any imperfect thing can be our universal grand righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness? no doubt it cannot: But you should prove that it cannot be a subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate conditional particular Righteousness.</p>
            <p>You do here confess that our Protestant Divines do call inherent Holiness, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical righteousness: Very good: I desire no more then those words contain: Yet I pray you confess that the Scripture commonly cals it so before them. 1 Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>justum fieri &amp; justificari,</hi> as to constitutive justification is all one. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that is righteous is doubtless justified <hi>constitutivè.</hi> And doubtless to be sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced just, and to be justified by sentence, is all one. And he that is first just by constitution, must needs be justified by sentence. But then all this is but <hi>in tantum:</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:39618:22"/>so far as he is just, so far he is undoubtedly <hi>justificatus constitutivè, &amp; justificandus per sententiam;</hi> and (as I said before) is it not as strange a righteousness which makes not a man righteous <hi>in tantum,</hi> (I speak of a formal Making) as a White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness that makes not white, or a <hi>Paternitas</hi> that makes not <hi>Patrem?</hi> 2. Do not all men know that (as Mr. <hi>Bradshaw</hi> saith) a very Reprobate may have some par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular righteousness? If you accuse <hi>Judas</hi> of killing the man that was slain yesterday, he is righteous as to this cause. Why then should you think the name of Righteousness so intollerable, when applied to faith and obedience.</p>
            <p>O but (saith a Learned man to me) then you ascribe but such a kind of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness to faith and obedience, as a Reprobate may have? that's a fair advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to faith. <hi>Ans.</hi> 1. Methinks then you should not say I am a Papist, and give too much to faith? 2. But consider, though both may have a <hi>justitiam particularem,</hi> yet to one it is in a case of no advantage to him: but in the other it is a condition of his eternal felicity, and so made by the Law of God. When salvation lies on one as a condition, and not on the other, I think there is much difference.</p>
            <p>Now to your third Argument, where you say, <hi>If the righteousness whereby we are justified, be the righteousness of God, then we are not justified by our obedience to Gospel-precepts: But,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Therefore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> All is of Gods gift. But in your sense I say, Our subordinate particular conditional Righteousness, is not the Righteousness performed by God without us: The word <hi>[by]</hi> therefore, and <hi>[Justified]</hi> and <hi>[Righteousness]</hi> must be distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished as before. All the rest of your words on this need no other answer, and I desire not to tire the Reader. The righteousness mentioned <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal: so was that which <hi>James</hi> speaks of when he saith, <hi>We are Justified by works:</hi> and that which <hi>John</hi> mentions, when he saith, <hi>He that doth Righteousness is Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> and fourty more.</p>
            <p>Your fourth Argument is this, <hi>If we are not Justified by two righteousnesses, existing in two distinct subjects, then our obedience to Gospel-precepts is not that righteousness whereby we are Justified: But,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Therefore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. To the Antecedent I say, of two coordinate righteousnesses it is true; but of two, whereof one is coordinate and the other subordinate, it is false, that there is not two. 2. But formally they are both in one subject: for it is We that are Righteous by Christs Righteousness: that is, by that which is Christs mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially, and in another numerical form; for surely one accident is not in two sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. But I say, materially one is in Christ, and the other in us.</p>
            <p>And here I remember an odd passage that you have, <hi>pag.</hi> 7. which I shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite. <hi>It doth not follow that Christs Righteousness cannot be imputed to us, before we have an actual created being, because Accidents cannot subsist without their sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: for as much as imputed righteousness is not an accident inherent in us, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently doth not necessarily require our existence. Christ is the subject of this Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, and the imputation of it as an act of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Hear all you that have been seduced by Mr. <hi>Eyre</hi> to believe that man was justified before he was born: Here he explaineth his mind to you. He said <hi>[man]</hi> but he meant <hi>[Christ.]</hi> If it be not we but Christ that is the subject, then doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less it is not <hi>we</hi> but <hi>Christ</hi> that hath the accident, and that is to be denominated by it: And then it is Christ that was righteous before we were born, and not we. Or else Christ makes us righteous, and yet we are not righteous, or we are righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and not righteous at once (even when we are not men) and that in respect of the same righteousness. When I read such passages as these, I understand the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:39618:23"/>meaning of your Patrons, that wonder men should seek to bring Gods Truths down to the reason of man: <hi>i.e.</hi> we must become bruits that we may become Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians (a horrid thing to speak;) and we must put out the eye of reason, that we may see with faith, which is the only supernatural elevation of reason.</p>
            <p>But you have an Argument <hi>pag.</hi> 57. to prove the assumption of your last <hi>viz. If by Christs Righteousness alone we are made perfectly Just and Righteous in the sight of God, then there is no other Righteousness which concurrs with his to our Justification: For what needs an addition to that which is perfect? But,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Therefore.</hi> All is granted, if you speak of the matter or form of our principal Righteousness; The Addition of a Condition is through no defect or imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in it: but God hath made it necessary to our participation of that which was not done by our selves, but by another. It is not true that we are made righteous by Christs Righteousness, till the condition be performed: but when it is performed, we are justified perfectly by Christs Righteousness alone, as to the principal general Justification; the condition performed being but a subservient particular righteousness. I would you would well consider, that Christ died to pardon nothing but our sins, and that he that hath nothing but sin, is not pardoned.</p>
            <p>You add, <hi>If we be Justified partly by Christs Righteousness, and partly by our own, then our saith for Justification must rely partly upon Christs Righteousness, and partly upon our selves: But,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Therefore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> I deny the Consequence. It is the relying on Christ that is our subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate righteousness it self: and therefore is such, because it is made the condition of our part in Christ: They are not coordinate, nor is faith our principal Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, but of a lower sort. God hath said, that if by faith we receive Christ, we shall be justified, and our faith shall be imputed to us for righteousness: but he hath never said, If we will rest on our own faith, we shall be righteous: For then resting on that faith would be a third sort of righteousness, subordinate to faith it self. These be but raw fancies.</p>
            <p>Your fifth Argument is, <hi>That which over throws the main difference between the Law and the Gospel, ought not to be admitted: for the confounding them will open an inlet to innumerable errors; nay by this means the Gospel it self will become a meer Cypher,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But the making our obedience to Gospel-Precepts the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness whereby we are Justified, overthrows the main difference between the Law and the Gospel: Therefore. For herein stands the chief agreement and difference between the Law and Gospel: They agree in this, That to Justification both do require the perfect fulfilling of the Law: But herein they differ, That the Law requireth to Justification, a Righteousness inherent in us, and perfect obedience to be performed in our own persons: The Gospel reveals for our Justification the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect righteousness of another, even of Christ, which is accepted in their behalf that do</hi> believe <hi>in him,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> These words which you cite out of Bishop <hi>Downham,</hi> say as I say in full sense; and say nothing to confirm your <hi>minor,</hi> which I deny, if you speak but of a subordinate particular righteousness: else I grant all. Do I say that we are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified by perfect obedience, which <hi>Downham</hi> speaks of? yea or by any in coordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation with Christ? If you understood the difference your self between the Law and Gospel, you would correct all these errors, and be a wiser man then I think either you or I are now. I pray you do me the favor as to consult but Mr. <hi>Pemble</hi> of justification, in the place cited even now (seeing you suppose him to be your
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:39618:23"/>own, but it seems disclaimed you a little before he went to heaven) and see how he differenceth the Law and the Gospel.</p>
            <p>You say, <hi>A defect in degrees is a sin against the Gospel,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> It is not a <hi>non</hi>-performance of the Gospel condition, and then it is no hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance to our Justification by it. Some Learned men have much boasted of that Argument <hi>[Obedience is it self imperfect, and therefore cannot be the condition of our Justification (as consummate at Judgement, or continued) for then what shall pardon the defects of it.]</hi> As if imperfect obedience might not be the condition of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of its own imperfections (subordinate to faith, as is said:) May not an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect faith be the condition of the pardon of its own imperfections?</p>
            <p>But to Mr. <hi>Eyre,</hi> who having done with me, adds. <hi>Now briefly my sense of this Proposition,</hi> [We are justified by faith] <hi>is no other then that which hath been given by all our Ancient Protestant Divines, who take saith herein objectively, not properly,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Our Divines take faith objectively, when the matter of our righteousness is spoken of; but how? Only by connotation of the object; and not by exclusion of faith it self: as if the word <hi>[Faith]</hi> signified Christ. Else you would fasten a strange sense on <hi>Paul,</hi> when it is said <hi>[If we believe it shall be imputed to us also,]</hi> doth the word <hi>[Believe]</hi> stand for the word <hi>[Christ?]</hi> But this our Divines have so fully confuted, that I will say no more to it but this, That if by <hi>[Believing]</hi> be not meant <hi>[Believing]</hi> but <hi>[Christ]</hi> when it is so many and many times rehears<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 1. Scripture is made the most useless unintelligible writing in the World, when no man can know the sense by the words a hundred times repeated. For your saying that <hi>Paul</hi> by <hi>Faith</hi> means not <hi>Faith,</hi> is no evidence to convince me. O how glad are the Papists of such expositions as yours, that may convince men that none can understand the Scripture without a Judge of its sense. 2. And then, why might it not as well be said that a man is justified by seeing Christ, or hearing him, or hearing of him, or any other act, as well as Believing, if it be not Believing that is meant, where it is spoken? But I will not anticipate Mr. <hi>Woodbridge</hi> in his work.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="section">
            <head>§ 6.</head>
            <p>THe next assault that I meet with is <hi>pag.</hi> 90, 91. where you say, <hi>Mr.</hi> B. (Thes. 70.) <hi>includes all works of obedience to Evangelical Precepts in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of saith, in which sense I presume no Papist will deny that we are Justified by faith alone, taking it as he doth, for</hi> fides formata, <hi>or saith animated with charity and other good works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Here is at least one untruth expressed, and another implied. 1. There is no mention in those words of mine of obedience to all Evangelical Precepts: but only of that sincere obedience which is made by God the condition of salvation. Now obedience may be sincere, and yet not be to all Precepts which are in the Gospel: Many a lesser particular duty may be unknown to one that obeys sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely: Mr. <hi>Eyre</hi> is bound by the Gospel to believe that faith goes before Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and yet he knows not this; may he not for all that obey sincerely? The Gospel requireth Baptism, and I think of Infants; yet it will not follow that no man is sincerely obedient that is unbaptized, as mistaking it to be now no duty, or that is against Infant-Baptism, on the like mistake.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:39618:24"/> 2. You intimate that it is our first justifying faith, or faith strictly taken that I here describe; and so add your parallel of the Papists. But honesty required you to have confessed on the contrary, that I had before spoke of faith in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per strict sense, as it is the condition upon which every man receiveth the Remis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of all the sins past of his whole life, and that Justification <hi>quoad statum,</hi> which some call Universal Justification, as distinct from particular Justification and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission following upon every new sin: and that in the words which you cite I only described faith in a more large improper sense, and as it is the condition on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of our glorification, and final Justification in the great Judgement. Why should you conceal this, and imply the contrary?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="section">
            <head>§. 7.</head>
            <p>THe next touch that I find is <hi>pag.</hi> 94. where you tell Mr. <hi>W.</hi> 2. <hi>If saith were a condition morally disposing us for Justification, we should then be concurrent causes with the Merits of Christ in procuring our Justification: for the Merits of Christ are not a Physical but a Moral cause, which obtain their effect by vertue of that Covenant which was made between him and the Father: now by ascribing unto faith a Moral Causal influx in our Justification, we do clearly put it</hi> in eodem ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere causae <hi>with the blood of Christ: which I hope Mr.</hi> W. <hi>will better consider of, before he engage too far in Mr.</hi> Baxters <hi>cause.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Because you are pleased to make it my cause, I will be bold to give my Reply. There are very palpable errors delivered with confidence in these words.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You confound moral <hi>Disposing,</hi> and moral <hi>Causing:</hi> All <hi>disposing</hi> is not <hi>causing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. You most falsly suppose that we ascribe to faith <hi>A moral causal in flux in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification:</hi> and do nothing to prove it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All is grounded on that gross Error, That <hi>all Civil or Legal conditions, are Moral Causes,</hi> which is so far from truth, that the clean contrary is true. <hi>No Civil or Legal condition,</hi> qua talis, <hi>is a Moral Cause.</hi> 1. A condition only while unperformed, suspendeth the act of the Law or Testament, that is, It was the Will of the Legislator or Testator, or Donor, that his Law, Testament, &amp;c. should act, or effect when the condition is performed, and not before: but not that it should be any cause: no more then <hi>quando venit dies</hi> the time is a cause. 2. A condition is but <hi>causa sine qua non;</hi> therefore it is no moral cause. Yet its true that among men, most conditions in another respect are moral causes; but none of them, <hi>as conditions.</hi> Men use to make somewhat a condition (though not alway) which is of worth to themselves, and so hath somewhat in the nature of the thing which is meritorious (when the condition is not casual, but Potestative or mixt:) and this is a Moral cause, not as it is a condition, but as meritorious. Would you have the world believe, without better manifestation, that you are so excellent a Lawyer, that we must take your word against common sense, and the common judgement of men that should be wiser in their own profession? You know sure that its common in the Civil Law to have cases of such casual conditions, as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be causal? As <hi>if such a Ship come into such a Harbour, such a day,</hi> being nothing to the Donors advantage. <hi>If such a son live to such an age, he shall have such Lands. If the Arrow that is shot up, fall within such a space.</hi> And the like is true in Potestative conditions (as they call them) that is, voluntary: <hi>I give thee a pardon on condition thou wilt accept it: or not refuse it: or not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefully
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39618:24"/>abuse me when I have given it thee: not spit in my face: not seek my life, ruine, dishonor, &amp;c.</hi> None of these are Meritorious, and therefore none of them causal.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Have you never observed that your friend Dr. <hi>Twiss</hi> doth not once or twice, but ordinarily, affirm that faith is a condition and <hi>medium</hi> of our justification, and that good works are <hi>causa dispositiva,</hi> and <hi>praeparatoria salutis?</hi> I may tell you more of his mind hereafter.</p>
            <p>One thing more in this Section I desire your resolution of. You here say, that <hi>the Merits of Christ are not a Physical but a Moral cause:</hi> upon which I would know; 1. Do not you take as much from it as I, and make the Merits of Christ as much a <hi>causa sine qua non in sensu physico,</hi> as I? For what can you do more then say it is no Physical cause at all? And with what justice or modesty then could you before pretend that I am worse in this very point then the Papists themselves, when I am no worse then you? A Moral causality I allow it, as well as you.</p>
            <p>Nay secondly give me leave to enquire whether in deed and truth you do allow it a Moral causality of our justification at all: In your <hi>page</hi> 66. you answer a shrewd Objection, which would prove you near to infidelity, <hi>viz. That you make void the Death of Christ: for if Justification be an immanent act in God, it is antecedent not only to faith, but to the Merits of Christ, which is contrary to many Scriptures, that do ascribe our Justification to his blood, as to a Meritorious cause.</hi> To which you Answer, <hi>That although Gods Will not to punish be antecedent to the death of Christ; yet for all we may be said to be Justified in him, because the whole effect of that Will is by and for the sake of Christ. As though Electing love precede the consideration of Christ,</hi> Ioh. 3.16. <hi>yet are we said to be chosen in him,</hi> Eph. 2.4. <hi>because all the Effects of that Love, are given by, and through, and for him. Gods</hi> not punishing <hi>us, is the fruits of his death: yet his Will not to punish, is antecedent thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> This distinction of <hi>Actus volentis,</hi> and <hi>res volita,</hi> we have oft here on such occasions. But 1. Do not you here make our active justification to be no fruit of Christs Merits at all, but only our passive? Now if you would publish this doctrine nakedly, That <hi>Justificatio Justificans,</hi> or Gods active Iustification, is not at all procured by Christ, it would be more candid and open dealing, then you use while you pretend so much to exalt Christs Merit, in your denying the parts or interest of faith and obedience.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Surely then we must find out another Active Iustification, whereof Christs Merits are the cause, as well as of the passive, if we will be ruled by Scripture; and this your Brethren have done, for which you oppose them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I would commend it to your consideration, Whether it be not a work worth your labour, the next time you set upon these imployments, to open to us like a Philosopher and Divine, how and in what sense and respect it is, that the Merits of Christ can cause the effect and not the act? the <hi>rem Volitam,</hi> and not the <hi>actum Volendi?</hi> And how Christs Merits can be a moral cause, or a meriting cause, and yet not cause the act of God? Merit you know is reckoned among the remote efficients of our pardon, and sanctification, and salvation. Now if God be the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er efficient, how can Merit which is the remote, cause these effects, and not cause Gods act? I would intreat you to answer it, as to all these effects, even Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and Glorification, as well as pardon. You know also, I suppose, that Merit
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:39618:25"/>is accounted one of the Procatarctical less-principal efficients; Now the nature of this cause is to incite the principal cause <hi>ad agendum</hi> extrinsically. And Merit is said to be that which moveth the agent <hi>ad talionem reddendam.</hi> Now if Christs Merits move not God as a Procatarctical cause, then how are they truly meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous causes? You know also, I doubt not, that a <hi>moral causing</hi> in such cases as ours about voluntarily Agents, doth consist in an argumentative, objective, or the like moral moving of the Agent. Now how can Christs Merits be moral causes here, and work nothing upon God the principal Cause? when this moral cause is a remote cause, and a remote cause produceth the effect <hi>mediâ causa propinquiore?</hi> I do not hereby conclude my self that Gods Will was moved by Christs Merits; but there is another wedge then yours by which we must cleave this knotty block; which if I tell you of, its like you will be prejudiced against it, because it is from me; but if you will study to expedite the business your self a little better then here you have done, it may reduce you to a better mind in the main. But if it should prove upon these considerations, that you do contradict your self, and do indeed deny Christ to be any cause, so much as Moral and Meritorious of justification active or passive, of the <hi>Actus volentis</hi> or <hi>Res volita,</hi> then I think you have been an unhappy exalter of Christ, while your zeal carried you against the Interest of faith.</p>
            <p>And methinks it should be scarce savoury to a friend of Christ and an exalter of his Merits, to have them made no more a cause of our justification, then of our Election; that is, of the effects of both which are in time, but of neither of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves which are from eternity.</p>
            <p>And I take it but for private Theology, that <hi>all the effects of electing love are given by, through and for Christ.</hi> Whereby you plainly intimate him to be the <hi>meritorious</hi> cause of the <hi>effects,</hi> which you deny of the <hi>Act.</hi> But 1. the giving of Christ himself is no small effect of electing love, and yet not given for and through himself. Christ was not given to Merit, for the sake of his Merit, as any efficient cause. 2. <hi>Adam</hi> and the Creation I think were not made upon the procurement of Christs Merits. 3. Nor was man endowed then with the Image of God. 4. Nor made Lord of the inferiour Creatures. 5 Nor placed in a Paradise. 6. Nor had the promise of immortality and felicity, if he sinned not; upon the procurement of the Merits of Christ. Yet all these were effects of electing love, being all means for the attainment of the ends of election. But many such things as these your Reader must bear with you in, unless he be a less scrupulous man, that can swallow all.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="section">
            <head>§. 8.</head>
            <p>THe next place that I find my self snapt at is <hi>pag</hi> 101 where you say, <hi>He gives us a youthfull frolike to shew his gallantry, like Mr.</hi> Baxters <hi>challenge,</hi> [Let the Antinomians shew one Scripture which speaks of Iustification from Eternity.] <hi>The Antinomians, saith he (Mr.</hi> W.) <hi>the Antipapists and Anti-Arminians he means) may read their eyes out, before they produce us one Text, for any other Iustification in Scripture, which is not by Faith or Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> This requires small answer. 1. Why could not such a rude challenge as this, once provoke you to open your Bible and transcribe one Text to that sense?
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39618:25"/>Had not one such Text been as soon cited, as all this book written? But some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is wanting? He that cannot say what he should, must say what he <hi>can,</hi> rather then yield or say nothing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I perceive it is not onely I that am a Papist or Arminian with you, or with whom an Antinomian signifies an Antipapist, and an Antiarminian? Mr. <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> fals under the same lash. But, Sir, while the Harmony of Confessions, and the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> and the late Confession of our Assembly are visible, the world hath a better character to know a Papist and Arminian by, then yours; and will hardly be perswaded that all are Papists and Arminians that hold not the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Justification or Remission, and that it is before the death and purchase of Christ, or that hold not that we are justified before we are men, or pardoned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have sinned; no nor all those that hold not the Justification of Infidels.</p>
            <p>But I perceive you are not sparing of your accusations of those that are not of your party and opinion; when <hi>pag.</hi> 84. you do so let fly at his Brother Mr. <hi>John Woodbridge</hi> forsooth
<q>[as no hearty friend to gathering and reforming Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, as deserting a Congregation in <hi>New-England,</hi> whereof he was Pastor, to become a Parish-Parson in the <hi>Old;</hi> and not onely so, but hath stood to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that parishes are true Churches.] And you say, [Its like his Parsonage is better, <hi>&amp;c</hi>]</q>
            </p>
            <p>Where 1. you venture to cast your censure upon the hidden thoughts of a mans heart, which is Gods prerogative: <hi>Who art thou that judgest another mans servant?</hi> Do you know that it was a better Parsonage that is the cause of what you men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? You that dare do this, dare do more. 2. If you deny that any Parishes, yea that many hundred Parlishes in <hi>England</hi> are true Churches, you do more then judge a particular Brother, and more then you are able to make good, and more then the Brethren of <hi>New-England</hi> would affirm. But I perceive your error is not a single one, not onely in Doctrinals: Separation will not perform in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion, what the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eading Dividers do promise.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 89, 90. Though I am not named, yet perhaps concerned, I am sure the truth is, where you say,
<q>[I desire the Reader to observe how much Mr. <hi>W.</hi> is beholden to a Popish Tenent, opposed (by all our Protestant Writers) to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port his cause, which is <hi>[That faith goes before Iustification to dispose us for it.] Bellarmine</hi> undertakes to prove, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Against whom all our Protestant Divines which my little Library hath obtained, do unanimously affirm, that faith doth not dispose or prepare us for Justification]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Like Cause, like carriage in maintaining it. 1. I suppose you know that our Divines do speak it of Justification in the Popish sense, which compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth sanctification and faith it self. But this you would not see or have your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der see. This is but <hi>pia fraus.</hi> 2. I suppose you know that our Divines by [Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position and preparation] do mean by way of condition <hi>sine quâ non;</hi> and so your Brethren teach as well as you, that faith the first grace, is given without any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>requisite condition on our parts, properly so called; the contrary is taught by Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagians, Jesuites and Arminians; but your pious fraud did hide this too. Is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the best Teaching? for error it is, but not for truth. Do you not know that the honest women of your Congregation that ever read Mr. <hi>Hookers Souls preparation for Christ,</hi> and <hi>Souls effectual Vocation,</hi> and <hi>Souls Justification,</hi> or <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Jo. Rogers of Faith,</hi> or M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Balton, Perkins,</hi> or the like honest old Practical Divines, could quickly confute your general assertion, and tell you, Sir, our Library is lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then yours, for all these Divines do tell us of a preparation necessary to Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39618:26"/>yea to faith it self; yea and they make this the great necessary doctrine for the breaking of hard hearts, and confuting the presumptions of the prophane. It is worth the observation of every honest Christian, how prophanness and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinomianism, do run hand in hand, and speak with one tongue, and put our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines to one and the same labour. So that in this point of preparation for Christ, and many others, we must confute the same conceits of both. 3. Nay sure you know that the generality of these Divines of ours, do make faith a condition, and most of them an instrument of our Justification: and an efficient cause is a little more then a passive preparation in <hi>sensu morali,</hi> by the act of faith.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="section">
            <head>§. 9.</head>
            <p>THe next place that I finde my name in, is, <hi>pag.</hi> 145. (and divers other places in the margin)
<q>[Our reconciliation is an immediate effect of the death of Christ, as Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> hath invincibly proved in his Answer to <hi>Baxter,</hi> p. 34.]</q> Thus you: and oft that Answer and Mr. <hi>Kendall</hi>'s is cited.</p>
            <p>To which I say but this. I so far abhor contention, and thirst after the Churches Peace, that I did impose it as a penalty on my self, not to answer that Book of Mr. <hi>Owens,</hi> till I saw a clear call proving it my duty, because I had been foolishly drawn to be the beginner of the Controversie: But I would not have you therefore talk of <hi>[Invincible proof]</hi> of such Tenets as these. Were that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend man and I to joyn Wit to Wit, and Learning to Learning, and the contest depended on the strength of the Contesters, I should easily yield that he were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible by such a one as I, and that the congress between him and me would be as unequal, as I too hastily said it would have been between Mr. <hi>Ball</hi> and him. But when I see what an advantage the Truth yields to a weak Defendor, and consider the disadvantage that he hath cast himself upon in that Book, I must profess to you, that I take it for as easie a thing to answer it sufficiently, almost as to write so much paper as that Answer will take up. You force me by your fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent references to that Book, to say this much, which else I would not have said, least I should exasperate. And for Mr. <hi>Kendall</hi> I have told you my thoughts of his Learned Notions more at large.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="section">
            <head>§. 10:</head>
            <p>THe next passage that toucheth me that I meet with, is <hi>pag.</hi> 174. where you say,
<q>[A Learned man of the late Assembly in a Sermon before the Parliament, then sitting, declared, that <hi>all</hi> the Promises of the New Covenant are Absolute, not only <hi>citra meritum,</hi> but <hi>citra conditionem,</hi> without any prerequired conditions of us: amongst many other places he cites this Text (Mr. <hi>Strong</hi> Serm. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30.) Besides this I might adde abundance more: But I believe Mr. <hi>Baxier</hi> is <hi>instar omnium</hi> with Mr. <hi>W.</hi>]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. I believe the plain Texts of Gods Word, not to be evaded with mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty is <hi>instar omnium</hi> with Mr. <hi>Woodbridge.</hi> He that reads his digested Sermon, and your acknowledgement of his supereminent parts, natural and acquired, will not believe that he takes his doctrine on trust from any man, much less from such a man as I. 2. It is great immodesty in you, if you intend hereby to perswade
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:39618:26"/>the world, that it is my singular opinion that the New Covenant hath conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yea or that the current of the Reformed Divines, and Churches do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly contradict your conceit. For me to prove this, were as needless as to heap up testimonies to prove that the Protestant Divines do hold that the Scripture is Gods Word. He that is ignorant of their judgement in this, let him be ignorant still for me. I except here three or four late Writers; especially those three <hi>Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vequerans Maccovius, Cocceius</hi> and <hi>Cloppenburgius.</hi> 3. But for Mr. <hi>Strong,</hi> I can say nothing, as having not his Sermon at hand; but what I have heard of the piety, Judgement &amp; Moderation of that Learned man, and what I finde of your bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in this Book in frequent untruths, I confess doth make me resolve rather to believe you wrong him, till I shall see the words; though not peremptorily to conclude it and charge you with it. I have oft my self maintained that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of the first Grace is Absolute; but I shall never believe that all the promises of the New Covenant are Absolute, as long as I take Gods Word for my Rule, which I hope will be till death. But here I must give you some Animadversions on your descriptions of a Condition, <hi>pag.</hi> 184.</p>
            <p>And to the first (out of Dr. <hi>Cawell</hi>) I say, that it be appointed for suspending the efficacy of the act or grant, is indeed essential to a condition: But that it be Uncertain is meerly accidentall; Uncertain is put for Contingent, because what is contingent is usually among men uncertain; It means an uncertainty <hi>in natura rei,</hi> when it may tend <hi>ad esse vel non esse;</hi> and not that it be <hi>actu incertum, id est, ignotum Donatori.</hi> Contingent things may be certain to God; and yet contingout in themselves still: As Dr. <hi>Twiss</hi> oft saith, He hath decreed not only that contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent things shall come to pass, but <hi>contingentia contingenter eventura.</hi> So doth he <hi>foreknow</hi> that contingent things shall contingently come to pass. Yet while they are contingent they are the fir matter for a condition, though he foreknow them. An unbeliever himself knows not that he shall believe. And if a man had a spirit of Prophesie to foreknow such future events, do you think that makes him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of making a conditional contract? If a Prophet had a House or Land to set, might he not make a Legal conditional Contract, because he foreknows the Rent will be paid? You may as well say, God should make no Law, because he foreknows it will be fulfilled, or men will do the thing commanded. But may he not therefore oblige them to do it? And if so, by a precept, I see not but the case is the same as to a sanction, and condition which is essential to that san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>And I must further tel you that you must not separate what God hath conjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. As he foreknows that we will perform the condition, so he foreknows that it will be a condition by his constitution before we perform it. For we cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form a condition which is no condition. And God did not forcknow that we should meerly perform the <hi>act</hi> of believing, but that we should perform the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> of believing: even as he did not only foreknow that we should perform the act of faith, but the duty of faith, and therefore that it must first be a duty.</p>
            <p>Moreover I would know whether ever God threatned an elect man or not in his Law, yea or the reprobate? If not, 1. How said he to <hi>Adam, In the day thou eatest thou shalt dye?</hi> 2. Then the first Law had no threatning (then which nothing more false) or else <hi>Adam</hi> was not elect. 3. How then are unbelievers condemned already. 4. There are an hundred express threatnings in the Word. 5. The contrary opinion is Antinomianism indeed, to take believers to be not at all threatned by the Law. 6. At least are they not threatned with temporal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:39618:27"/>or chastisements? 7. And then wicked reprobates are not threatned, which is false.</p>
            <p>If you grant the threatning to the Elect or others, then it is either a conditional threatning or Absolute: If Absolute then they must bear it: there is no escape; nor are all absolute to them that must bear it. If conditional: then either God knows whether they will commit that sin which is the condition of the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or he doth not. The later you will disclaim I doubt not: The former grants that there may be a condition which is yet certainly foreknown to God.</p>
            <p>You will find the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> making a conditional contract by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, in a case wherein God had before revealed to him the event.</p>
            <p>If (as Dr. <hi>Twiss</hi> hath well proved) the same thing may be necessary and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent, then the same thing may be necessary, foreknown, and yet conditionally given out or threatned in Law.</p>
            <p>It is a most dangerous course of Divines to set Gods Derrees, Foreknowledge or Disposal of Events, in opposition to his moral Rectorship, as if the acts of one must be inconsistent with the acts of the other. Let me speak it out, though to the provocation of the contemptuous and self-conceited, that this one grand mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stake, hath introduced most of their Errors, and feedeth most of your contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. They cannot reconcile the acts of Gods absolute Dominion, with the moral acts of Regiment; nor can they see in what a distinct series they stand.</p>
            <p>The like Answer serves to the same word <hi>[incertum]</hi> in the next definition of <hi>Cook.</hi> Your two later I wholly allow of, interpreting <hi>[by performance]</hi> to mean <hi>[upon performance.]</hi> Your conclusion <hi>pag.</hi> 185. is false, that <hi>Omnis conditio ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedens est effectiva.</hi> Though I remember <hi>Chamier</hi> hath such a word, but enough to the contrary.</p>
            <p>I have spoke thus much of this, that you may also see, that though the Truths in Mr. <hi>Owens</hi> Book are Invincible, yet the Mistakes are not; and if you will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider it well, I think you will find that the pulling out of this one Pin, hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed his Fabrick to fall in pieces. For my part I profess to follow my conscience, which upon the most impartial search of Scripture that I am able to make, doth tell me that the Scripture doth so evidently contain conditional threatnings and promises to the Elect, that to deny it, would be, to me, to renounce my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, and proclaim Scripture to be utterly unintelligible, which were to be no Word of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="section">
            <head>§. 11.</head>
            <p>YEt you have not done with me: for <hi>pag.</hi> 190. you fall on without fear or— that the end may be like the beginning. You say, 1. <hi>That the Papists assert no other works and condition to be necessary to our Justification and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation then what our adversaries do.</hi> 2. <hi>Neither Papists nor Arminians do ascribe any more Meritoriousness to Works then our opponents, &amp;c. And in this sense Mr.</hi> Baxter <hi>will tell you that the performers of a condition may be said to merit the Reward. The Papists never pleaded for Merit upon any other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. If this be true, our Divines are notorious liars and slanderers, so frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to charge them with more. Which yet I had rather of the two believe of Mr. <hi>Eyre</hi> then of them, if I must needs do one. 2. If this be true, the Papists are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:39618:27"/>notorious liars and slanderers, to wrong one another so much as they do, by as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming more of one another. 3. If this be true, doth not Mr. <hi>Eyre</hi> speak better of the Papists then we are use to hear? and should not all honest men be glad to hear that so great a part of Christendome, are far better men then we took them for? 4. Doth not this intimate; Why may not the Papists be encouraged and have liberty in <hi>England</hi> as well as we, <hi>R. B.</hi> and a hundred Divines that say as much as he? Especially if you compare this passage with what he saith to Mr. <hi>W.</hi> pag. 117. <hi>[I dare say a more unsound Assertion cannot be picked out of the Writings either of Papists or Arminians then this is.]</hi> And why then should not we be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected a like, if we be corrupted a like? Whether he mean that we should be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained as they, I know not well; but by his Epistle to the Parliament it is liker he means that they should have Liberty as well as we. You that are Mr. <hi>Eyre</hi> his neighbours, wrong him sorely if you think him a friend to Popery, you may see the Papists will endure you to call Mr. <hi>W.</hi> and I, and all the Reformed Churches, Papists, if you will but open the door and let them in, and help them in weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our hands and resisting us in the work of Christ.</p>
            <p>You adde,
<q>[Though Mr. <hi>B.</hi> seems to mince the matter, calling his conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons but a <hi>sine qua non,</hi> and a Pepper co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he attributes as much, if not more to Works then the Papists, Arminians and Socinians have done. The Papists will not say that Works do merit in a strict and proper sense.]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Prov. 19.5. <hi>A salse witness shall not be unpun shed, and he that speaketh lies shall not escape.</hi> Though I delay this business purposely till I come to Mr. <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> yet I will give the Reader one word here before hand.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Out of one of their own; <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (Printed <hi>Ingolst.</hi> 80 1605) <hi>pag.</hi> 2567, 2568, &amp;c. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>de Justifie.</hi> thus determineth this Question <hi>[Ʋtrum opera Bona sint Meritoria ex condigno ratione pacti tantum? an ratione operis tantum? an ratione utrins{que}?] Media sententia nobis videtur probabilior, quae docet, Opera bona Justorum Meritori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> esse vitae aeternae ex condigno, ratione pacti &amp; operts simul,</hi> &amp;c.] And <hi>p.</hi> 2571, 2572, he bringeth seven Arguments to prove that <hi>in opere bono ex Gratia precedente, est quaedam proportio &amp; aequalitas ad praemium vitae aeternae.</hi> And <hi>li.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 21. <hi>pag.</hi> 2208, 2209. he endeavoureth to prove <hi>[Meritum de congruo fundari in aliqua Dignitate operis potius quam in promissione.]</hi> Judge now Reader, what cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit is to be given to Mr. <hi>Eyre</hi>'s words? and how dangerous a thing this Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian conceit is, that sin is all pardoned before we repent or are born. Durst such a pious man as this else over and over, even here on one page repeat in Print so notorious a falshood? and say, [Neither Papists nor Arminians ascribe any more Meritoriousness to Works] then we do? Nay that [I attribute as much, if not more to Works then the Papists.] Was <hi>Bellarmine</hi> no Papist? I deny all Merit to our Faith or Works; unless by the word [Merit] you mean somewhat that is not Merit. Doth <hi>Bellarmine</hi> do so? Nay he saith again here [The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist never pleaded for Merit upon any other Account] then <hi>ex pacto.</hi> The Lord pardon this audacious falshood to you Brother, and humble you for it.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>Bellarmine</hi> be no Papist with you, what say you by <hi>Aquinas?</hi> See him 1.2 <hi>ae. q.</hi> 114. <hi>art.</hi> 1. <hi>c. &amp; art.</hi> 3. <hi>c. [Si consideretur secundum operis substantiam &amp; secundum quod procedit ex libero arbitrio, sic non potest ibi esse condignitas propter maximam inae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitatem: Sed est ibi congruitas propter quandam aequalitatem proportionis. Si autem loquamur de opere Meritorio secundum quod procedit ex gratia Spiritus sancti, sic est Meritorium vitae aeternae ex condigno: sic enim Valor meriti attenditur secund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m virtutem Spiritus sansti moventis nos in vitam aeternam,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:39618:28"/> 3. The world knows that the Papists have commonly maintained (I say not, every man of them) the Merit of congruity, the very nature of which they ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narlly affirm to be from the respect of the work it self, and not from the Pact or Promise.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Our Divines commonly charge them with more. <hi>Perkins</hi> Reformed <hi>Cathol. of Merit, Vol.</hi> 1 <hi>p.</hi> 574, 545 saith, [The Popish Church placeth Merits within man, making two sorts thereof: the Merit of the person, and the Merit of the work: The Merit of the work is a dignity or excellency in the work, whereby it is made fit and enabled to deserve Life Everlasting for the doer: And Works, as they teach, are meritorious two waies. 1. By Covenant, because God hath made a promise of Reward to them. 2. By their own dignity: For Christ hath merited that our Works might merit: And this is the substance of their Doctrine.] So far <hi>Perkins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will adde no more, but leave it to the consideration of Mr. <hi>Eyre</hi>'s Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members, whether for this publique sin, they ought not to admonish him, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire him publiquely to profess his repentance? If not, let them at least see the evil fruits of his Doctrine, and that all his words are not to be believed Its scarce likely that he will make much more conscience of an untruth in the Pulpit, then in the Press; the later being the most publique, and therefore should be most advised and cautelous way of delivering our minds.</p>
            <p>Yet he is at it again before he comes to the end of the same Page, saying,
<q>[But now Mr. <hi>B.</hi> goes a step beyond them, in that he ascribes a Meritoriousness to Works, which the Arminians and Socinians have not dared to do.]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> I am glad this is the last place where I find my self named. For I love not above all Writings to deal with those which are capable of no other Answer for substance, then that one <hi>Word</hi> by which the fellow confuted all <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> Methinks it fouls my mouth, so much as to tell you what your words are; and it cannot but be unsavoury and unprofitable to the Reader; and therefore I shall say no more to you; but heartily desire the Lord to recover and forgive you, and to that end to make you ask forgiveness believingly and penitently, and to that end to convince you that you are guilty, till forgiveness come, and that no Infidels or Impenitent Rebels are forgiven: And I heartily desire, that if you preach this to your people, which you publish in this Book, the sad effects of it may never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in their hearts and lives, but that Gods truth may lye neerer their hearts and prevail, and the face of your doctrine may not be seen in the face of your hearters conversation or your own.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:39618:28"/>
            <head>Novemb. 26. 1653.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>VNderstand, that for all the hot words between us, Mr.</hi> Eyre <hi>and I are agreed, if he be a man to be believed. For</hi> pag. 67. <hi>he hath these words,</hi> [However were the thing it self granted, That there was in God from Everlasting an Absolute, Fixed and Immutable Will never to deal with his people according to their sins, but to deal with them as Righteous persons, this Controversie were ended.]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Supposing that it is in regard of eternal punishment that he speaks, and not of meer Legal Obligations, Convictions or Condemnations by Law, Conscience, or men (in all which respects God deals not with the unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous as with righteous men) I do grant the whole, and here subscribe my concession: and so if Mr.</hi> E. <hi>be a man of his word,</hi> The Controversie is Ended.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Rich. Baxter.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:39618:29"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39618:29"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecause M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               </hi> Eyre <hi>hath the modesty to alleadge M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               </hi> Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therfords <hi>Judgement for his Opinion, I intreat thee to get and reade a full Volume of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               </hi> Rutherfords <hi>(which I had forgotten when I cited those words before) called</hi> [A Survey of the Spiritual Antichrist: opening the Secrets of Familism and Antinomianism, <hi>against M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               </hi> Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marsh, <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               </hi> Dell, Town, <hi>D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               </hi> Crispe, H. Den, Eaton, <hi>&amp;c. in which is revealed the Rise and Spring of Antinomians, Familists, Libertines,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is not only as against M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               </hi> Eyre<hi>'s Testimony that I desire this of thee, but especially because it is one of the fullest Books that I know extant, against the Errors of this Sect; and very usefull to the godly in these seducing times.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:39618:30"/>
            <head>READER,</head>
            <p>SInce this Book was Printed I am able to give thee a more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain account of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Crandon</hi>'s Learned Examination of my <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorisms:</hi> If thou wouldst know the Contents, I'le tell thee the main substance of this Book in one word, <hi>viz. [That I am a Papist, and one of the worser sort of them too.]</hi> This one dish adorned with the flowers of <hi>Billingsgate</hi> Rhetorick, and sawced with many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred palpable falshoods, is the precious feast which M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Eyre</hi> hath invited thee to. But if thou think that I tell thee this for my own ends, and as envying thee such felicity as the reading of his Volume, take thy course, and believe me when thou hast tried, <hi>Fisher, Haggar, Reyes,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Eyre,</hi> and all that have opened their mouths against me, are but meal-mouth'd fellows to this M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Crandon.</hi> But if it work on thee as it did on me, thou wilt have some mirth at least for thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: For I confess I was not able to forbear laughter to see the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous monster come forth, and act such a Tragedy before my face: Nor can I yet forbear when I cast my eye on it, and think how seriously the man perswades me that I am a Papist. But then remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that thy mirth must cost thee sorrow, as mine doth, when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider that I laugh at the signes of a mans misery, and at that which discovereth our common depravedness, and the misery of our poor people that must be both corrupted and distracted by such Teachers as these. But if thou have a minde to learn M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Crandon</hi>'s Ethicks, or Theology, take them and make thy best of them; but I pray thee expect not that ever I should particularly Reply to it, till I have so much time that I know not how better to spend, or dare give an account to God of such an expence of it, and till I am more inclined to stirre in such a puddle as that is. If thou be not able to confute M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Crandon</hi>'s strong lines without my help, its not long of me, nor can I have while to help thee, though I pity thee: Yet lest thou say I shift it off, I intend God willing, to give thee that which shall be the matter of an Answer, to the exceptions of him and many others, even a plain and full Confession of my Faith, and especially in the
<pb facs="tcp:39618:30"/>Point in question: How much it is that I ascribe to man or any of his actions in the work of Justification? with so much more against the main charges of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Cr.</hi> and M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Eyre,</hi> as shall give thee cause enough to lament, that Opinion, Faction, and Passion, should make Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans so cruel to their own consciences, as these men have been; and shall convince thee, that whatever they do by the rest of the Law, the ninth Commandment is used but little better by them, then the second is by the Papists. For all these crying sins, I am in hope, by their zealous pretendings to the honour of Free-Grace, that they mean well in the main: And then I desire those that fear God to consider, what crooked pieces the best of us are, what need we have of daily pardon of sin, and what great cause to bear with abundance of darkness even in Teachers themselves, and to put up many and great injuries from one another, if ever we expect any quietness to the Church: and not only to see that we forgive them our selves, but also to pray for them in imitation of our Lord, <hi>[Father, forgive them, for they know not what they do.]</hi> And though M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Eyre</hi> hath clawed his Brother with this commendations, that he is <hi>[a faithful servant of Jesus Christ, and a workman that need not be ashamed.]</hi> Yet I intreat M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Cr.</hi> to see that he be not hardened in impenitency by this warrant: For M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>E.</hi> cannot secure him hereby from future shame, though he may do somewhat to destroy the remnants of his present modesty. If such a mass of Railing Accusation, that is, Slander and Reviling twisted together, be the work of [A Workman that need not be ashamed] I confess I know not what men should be ashamed of and must say, that such men are not over-bashfull. Indeed if there were no Law, and so no transgression, they might prove that they need not be ashamed: Or had they well proved that all their sinne was perfectly pardoned before they were born, I should yield that they need not be ashamed, so far as shame is a punishment for sinne: and therefore must cease upon a perfect Remission. But Impenicency and Impudency have no good foundation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>